<thepianist>
    <piece name="Tango" componist="Albeniz, I." midifile="078.MID" photo="albeniz.jpg">
        Tango is a charming little piece from Isaac Albeniz's Album of 
        Eight Pieces. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Aria (Goldberg Variations)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="207.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Because of the two recordings by the late pianist Glenn Gould, J.S. 
        Bach's Goldberg Variations have achieved a virtual "pop" music status. 
        Gould's original version was actually the first classical hit record the 
        1960's. Bach, it is said, was commissioned to compose these 30 variations 
        for performance by Johann Goldberg (to help cure his patron Count 
        Keyserling of insomnia). It is this Aria which begins and ends the whole 
        cycle.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fugue (WTC Bk. 1, No. 3)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="109.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        The matching fugue to Prelude No. 3 (WTC Bk. 1) is in three voices 
        and is both rhymically vigorous and cheerful.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fugue (WTC Bk. 1, No. 5)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="111.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        The matching four voice Fugue to Bach's Prelude No. 5 (WTC, Bk. 
        1) has a rhythmically agressive, snapping theme which energizes then 
        whole thing.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fugue (WTC Bk. 1, No. 7)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="113.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        The Fugue from the Prelude and Fugue No. 7, Book 1 of the Well-
        Tempered Clavier is cheerful and spritely. It is in three voices.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fugue (WTC Bk. 1, No.21)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="023.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        This matching Fugue to Bach's Prelude No. 21 in B-flat (WTC Bk. 
        1) is in three voices and carries itself with thoughtful elegance. It is not 
        technically difficult.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Gavotte (French Suite No. 5)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="196.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Bach composed six Suites of dances in the French style. No. 5 in G major is considered the finest of
        the set. The Gavotte movement is clear and delicate, and a delight to the ears.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Italian Concerto, Mvt. 1" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="131.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        The Italian Concerto, regarded as one of Bach's best single pieces, 
        was published in 1735 as Concerto in the Italian Manner. It is a piece 
        meant for solo performance on a harpsichord with two keyboards. One 
        keyboard emulates the orchestral tutti against which the other keyboard 
        plays the solo part. In typical Italian concerto style, the piece is written in 
        three movements: the Allegro, the Andante, and the Presto.
         The first movement is played at an allegro tempo. The solo melodic voice 
        is played against a battery of robust, Italian-style chords.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Italian Concerto, Mvt. 2" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="132.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        The Italian Concerto, regarded as one of Bach's best single pieces, 
        was published in 1735 as Concerto in the Italian Manner. It is a piece 
        meant for solo performance on a harpsichord with two keyboards. One 
        keyboard emulates the orchestral tutti against which the other keyboard 
        plays the solo part. In typical Italian concerto style, the piece is written in 
        three movements: the Allegro, the Andante, and the Presto.
         The Andante movement of Bach's Italian-style concerto uses syncopation 
        and recitatives to create a dramatic mood and lyrical melody.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Italian Concerto, Mvt. 3" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="133.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
         The Italian Concerto, regarded as one of Bach's best single pieces, 
        was published in 1735 as Concerto in the Italian Manner. It is a piece 
        meant for solo performance on a harpsichord with two keyboards. One 
        keyboard emulates the orchestral tutti against which the other keyboard 
        plays the solo part. In typical Italian concerto style, the piece is written in 
        three movements: the Allegro, the Andante, and the Presto.
         In this joyful Presto final movement, Bach deliberately and skillfully 
        places musical opposition between the soloist and tutti accompaniment.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Jesu Joy of Man's Desiring" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="003.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Jesu Joy of Man's Desiring (Jesu, belibet meine Freude) from Canata 
        no. 147 is one of J.S. Bach's most famous chorale melodies. It was 
        originally composed for trumpet, oboe, strings and organ, but is perhaps 
        best known in this arrangement written by British pianist Dame Myra Hess 
        (1890-1965). In the early 1900's, Hess perservered with what was to 
        become the more modern style of performance which emphasized clarity, 
        balance, faithfulness to the written manuscript rather than the pianist's 
        personal display. She was outmuscled for many years by more flamboyant 
        pianists, but did not abandon her career, achieving world stature by the 
        1920's. Hess built her repertoire around composers such as Bach, Mozart, 
        Beethoven, Brahms and Schubert. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="March in D" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="063.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
         Bach's March in D is from the Anna Magdalena Notebook, 
        composed by Bach for his second wife to help her with her harpsichord 
        lessons. The quarter notes in the left hand keep the time as the spritely 
        melody marches forward.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Minuet in G" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="061.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Bach's Minuet in G is from the Anna Magdalena Notebook, 
        composed by Bach for his second wife to help her with her harpsichord 
        lessons. It remains very popular with keyboard students to this day.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Minuet in G (2)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="062.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Bach's Minuet in G is from the Anna Magdalena Notebook, 
        composed by Bach for his second wife to help her with her harpsichord 
        lessons. Its lilting, tuneful melody has made it very popular with keyboard 
        students to this day.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Musette in D" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="064.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Bach's Musette in D is from the Anna Magdalena Notebook, 
        composed by Bach for his second wife to help her with her harpsichord 
        lessons. Musette is what they used to call a bagpipe in France. The baroque 
        court dance of the same name always has a left hand "drone" (usually in 
        fifths or an octave) which imitates a bagpipe. Listen for the left hand 
        octaves and the surprising little jumps for both hands.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude (WTC Bk. 1, No. 3)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="108.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Wohltemperiertes Klavier, or Well-Tempered Clavier, was 
        published by Bach in two volumes of 24 Preludes and Fugues each. The 
        first was released in 1722, and the second around 1740. By using all major 
        and minor keys, this collection of works was taking advantage of a new 
        advance in keyboard technology: tempered tuning. A "tempered" keyboard 
        allowed performance in any key without retuning the instrument--
        something that had previously been impossible.
         Prelude No. 3 in C-sharp from Book 1 of the WTC is a sparkling little 
        gem that seems a continuous flow of sixteenth notes.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude (WTC Bk. 1, No. 5" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="110.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Bach's Prelude from the Prelude and Fugue No. 5 (from Book 1 of 
        the Well-Tempered Clavier) is a masterpiece of contrast. The lilting 
        Prelude contrasts sharply with the dotted rhythms of the Fugue.
         Wohltemperiertes Klavier, or Well-Tempered Clavier, was published by 
        Bach in two volumes of 24 Preludes and Fugues each. The first was 
        released in 1722, and the second around 1740. By using all major and 
        minor keys, this collection of works was taking advantage of a new 
        advance in keyboard technology: tempered tuning. A "tempered" keyboard 
        allowed performance in any key without retuning the instrument-- 
        something that had previously been impossible.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude (WTC Bk. 1, No. 7)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="112.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        The Prelude No. 7 in E flat from Book 1 of the Well-Tempered 
        Clavier is both melodic and inspired. Its wide variety of textures include 
        both improvised-sounding and imitative passages.
         Wohltemperiertes Klavier, or Well-Tempered Clavier, was published by 
        Bach in two volumes of 24 Preludes and Fugues each. The first was 
        released in 1722, and the second around 1740. By using all major and 
        minor keys, this collection of works was taking advantage of a new 
        advance in keyboard technology: tempered tuning. A "tempered" keyboard 
        allowed performance in any key without retuning the instrument--
        something that had previously been impossible.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude (WTC Bk. 1, No.21)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="022.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        Bach's Prelude No. 21 in B-flat (WTC BK 1) is a sparkling, toccata-
        like work with a true improvisary feeling. The left hand punctuates the 
        beats while the right hand completes broken chords with almost tremolo 
        speed. It is a roller coaster ride from beginning to end, with but the 
        slightest hesitation before the final roll. 
         Wohltemperiertes Klavier, or Well Tempered Clavier, was published by 
        Bach in two volumes of 24 Preludes and Fugues each. The first was 
        released in 1722, and the second around 1740. By using all major and 
        minor keys, this collection of works was taking advantage of a new 
        advance in keyboard technology: tempered tuning. A "tempered" keyboard 
        allowed performance in any key without retuning the instrument--
        something that had previously been impossible.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in C (WTC) Bk.1)" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="212.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        J.S. Bach's Prelude in C (WTC Bk. 1) is made up of a simple but 
        subtly stirring series of arpeggiated chords. There is no actual melody, 
        however, one can feel melodic movement. In the 19th century, Franz 
        Schubert used this Prelude as the accompaniment for his song Ave Maria 
        (Liszt's arrangement of his arrangement is included in The Pianist).
         Wohltemperiertes Klavier, or Well Tempered Clavier, was published by 
        Bach in two volumes of 24 Preludes and Fugues each. The first was 
        released in 1722, and the second around 1740. By using all major and 
        minor keys, this collection of works was taking advantage of a new 
        advance in keyboard technology: tempered tuning. A "tempered" keyboard 
        allowed performance in any key without retuning the instrument--
        something that had previously been impossible. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Toccata and Fugue in d" componist="Bach, J.S." midifile="203.MID" photo="bach.jpg">
        The celebrated Toccata and Fugue in D minor for organ has long 
        considered to be one of J.S. Bach's most accessible and popular works. 
        Today, there is some question as to whether Bach actually wrote the work. 
        Nevertheless, its drama and brilliance remain. Virtuoso pianist Ferruccio 
        Busoni (1866-1924) wrote this difficult piano transcription.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Islamey" componist="Balakirev" midifile="130.MID" photo="balakirev.jpg">
        Islamey by Mily Balakirev (1837-1910) may be one of the most 
        difficult piano works ever composed and is thus rarely heard in concert. It 
        was composed in 1869 and based on themes from Armenia and the
        Caucasus region. There is an abundance of Lisztian technical challenges. 
        Two oriental-type themes are given a series of difficult variations. In 1908, 
        Islamey was orchestrated by Alfredo Casella.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Bagatelle, op. 33, no. 1" componist="Beethoven" midifile="197.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        Beethoven wasn't always fire and brimstone. In his little Bagatelles for piano, the old master showed his 
        lighter side. The Bagatelle in E flat, Op. 33, No. 1 has a dance-like lilt punctuated by graceful and sometimes 
        surprising scale runs.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Bagatelle, op. 33, no. 4" componist="Beethoven" midifile="198.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        Beethoven wasn't always fire and brimstone. In his little Bagatelles for piano, the old master showed his 
        lighter side. The Bagatelle in A major, Op. 33, No. 4 flows at a relaxing pace and with graceful charm.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fuer Elise" componist="Beethoven" midifile="001.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        Beethoven's Bagatelle in a (Fuer Elise) was composed on April 27,
        1810 as a leaf in an album. Ludwig Nohl, who discovered the manuscript 
        and published it in 1867, appears to have misread Beethoven's writing of 
        the name "Therese" (von Brunswick). She was the woman Beethoven 
        reputedly loved and it was in her papers that the manuscript of Fuer Elise 
        was discovered. It is one of the very best known and loved short works for 
        piano. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Moonlight Sonata, Op. 27, No. 2, Mvt. 1" componist="Beethoven" midifile="137.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        In 1802, Beethoven's Sonatina Quasi una Fantasia was published 
        under the subtitle Moonlight. Beethoven's publishers were prompted to dub 
        the sonata "Moonlight" by Heinrich Rellstab, who wrote that the first 
        movement inspired the vision "of a boat on Lake Lucerne by a luminous 
        night." The Moonlight Sonata in C sharp minor, Op. 27, was dedicated to 
        one of Beethoven's many loves: the Countess Giulietta Guicciardi. Upon 
        hearing the Moonlight Sonata, the listener is repeatedly reminded of 
        Beethoven's remarkable emotive humanity.
         By beginning the Moonlight Sonata with a movement played Adagio 
        sostenuto, Beethoven broke with traditional sonata form. Expessively lyric, 
        this first movement is written in slow, melodic, eighth-note triplets, giving 
        the piece a tranquil sadness.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Moonlight Sonata, Op. 27, No. 2, Mvt. 2" componist="Beethoven" midifile="138.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        In 1802, Beethoven's Sonatina Quasi una Fantasia was published 
        under the subtitle Moonlight. Beethoven's publishers were prompted to dub 
        the sonata "Moonlight" by Heinrich Rellstab, who wrote that the first 
        movement inspired the vision "of a boat on Lake Lucerne by a luminous 
        night." The Moonlight Sonata in C sharp minor, Op. 27, was dedicated to 
        one of Beethoven's many loves: the Countess Giulietta Guicciardi. Upon 
        hearing the Moonlight Sonata, the listener is repeatedly reminded of 
        Beethoven's remarkable emotive humanity.
         Franz Liszt described the second movement of Beethoven's Moonlight 
        Sonata as "a flower between abysses". The lively and invigorating scherzo 
        is played Allegretto and contrasts brightly against the darker first and 
        second movements that surround it.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Moonlight Sonata, Op. 27, No. 2, Mvt. 3" componist="Beethoven" midifile="142.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        In 1802, Beethoven's Sonatina Quasi una Fantasia was published 
        under the subtitle Moonlight. Beethoven's publishers were prompted to dub 
        the sonata "Moonlight" by Heinrich Rellstab, who wrote that the first 
        movement inspired the vision "of a boat on Lake Lucerne by a luminous 
        night." The Moonlight Sonata in C sharp minor, Op. 27, was dedicated to 
        one of Beethoven's many loves: the Countess Giulietta Guicciardi. Upon 
        hearing the Moonlight Sonata, the listener is repeatedly reminded of 
        Beethoven's remarkable emotive humanity.
         The third movement, a restless Presto agitato, expresses the drama found 
        in the first movement, but in a more animated fashion. It is tumultuous and 
        stormy, as well as tragic. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Pathetique Sonata, Op. 13, Mvt. 1" componist="Beethoven" midifile="134.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        The Sonata in C minor, op. 13, is one of Beethoven's most 
        celebrated and popular works. Subtitled Path tique by Beethoven's 
        publishers, it was originally dedicated to Prince Karl von Lichnowski in 
        1799. Its subtitle, a French adjective meaning "moving" or "touching", 
        describes the prevailing mood of this sonata. At once, the sonata expresses 
        Beethoven's sadness, and defiance of the deafness which was gradually 
        engulfing him.
         The first movement is prefaced by a slow and dramatic introduction, 
        intended to dominate the entire piece with tragic and melancholy 
        overtones. This powerful introduction is echoed in the Allegro second 
        theme, an agitated illustration of sadness and futility.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Pathetique Sonata, Op. 13, Mvt. 2" componist="Beethoven" midifile="135.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        The Sonata in C minor, op. 13, is one of Beethoven's most 
        celebrated and popular works. Subtitled Path tique by Beethoven's 
        publishers, it was originally dedicated to Prince Karl von Lichnowski in 
        1799. Its subtitle, a French adjective meaning "moving" or "touching", 
        describes the prevailing mood of this sonata. At once, the sonata expresses 
        Beethoven's sadness, and defiance of the deafness which was gradually 
        engulfing him.
         The second movement of the Path tique, in magnificent rondo form, is 
        played Adagio cantabile. It has a definite lyrical quality.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Pathetique Sonata, Op. 13, Mvt. 3" componist="Beethoven" midifile="136.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
        The Sonata in C minor, op. 13, is one of Beethoven's most 
        celebrated and popular works. Subtitled Path tique by Beethoven's 
        publishers, it was originally dedicated to Prince Karl von Lichnowski in 
        1799. Its subtitle, a French adjective meaning "moving" or "touching", 
        describes the prevailing mood of this sonata. At once, the sonata expresses 
        Beethoven's sadness, and defiance of the deafness which was gradually 
        engulfing him.
         The third and final movement of the Path tique is a classic Rondo and is 
        consummated by a grandiose coda.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Symphony No. 5, Mvt. 1" componist="Beethoven" midifile="200.MID" photo="beethoven.jpg">
         Very little explanation is needed for the first movement of Beethoven's venerable Fifth Symphony. 
        Liszt, who often wrote difficult but faithful piano arrangements of popular symphonic or operatic works 
        (generally for use in his own concerts), put his pen to paper in this impressive transcription. Incidentally, he 
        did piano arrangements of all the Beethoven symphonies.
        The twenty-four Preludes were composed from 1836-9 and first 
        published in 1839. Like Bach's Preludes from the Well-Tempered Clavier 
        (upon which these were modelled), Chopin composed one in each major 
        and minor key. Often the prelude is based on a single idea, sometimes only 
        a motive. They are true romantic miniatures, each pointedly expressing a 
        feeling or idea. They work as individual pieces, but when played as a set, 
        they display a true, cohesive emotional spectrum of the highest artistry.
         Prelude No. 4 in E minor is a simple, sadly expressive melody floating 
        over repeated left hand chords.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Minuet" componist="Boccherini" midifile="077.MID" photo="boccheini.jpg">
        Luigi Boccherini (1743-1805) was a contemporary of Haydn and his 
        music is tuneful with adventurous harmonies. The famous Minuet, heard 
        here in piano arrangement, is actually a movement from one of his string 
        quartets.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Ballade in d, Op. 10, No. 1" componist="Brahms" midifile="107.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Brahms' Four Ballades, Op. 10 (composed in 1856) were inspired by the Scotch Ballade "Edward". No.
        1, the Ballade in D minor blends feelings of sad tragedy with heroism.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Ballade in g, Op. 118, No. 3" componist="Brahms" midifile="032.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Some of the most moving works of Brahms' distinguished 
        composing career are the short piano works he wrote late in his life.  The 
        six pieces Opus 118 were composed  in 1892 when Brahms was 59 years 
        old. No. 3, the Ballade in G minor has an exciting chordal opening theme 
        and a lovely duet-like middle section.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Capriccio in b,op. 76 no. 2" componist="Brahms" midifile="199.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Brahms' popular Capriccio in B minor is a test of a pianist's staccato touch and has a playfulness in 
        keeping with the name. It is part of a set of eight short piano pieces composed between 1871-78 and published 
        as Opus 76. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Intermezzo in A, Op. 118, No. 2" componist="Brahms" midifile="031.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Some of the most moving works of Brahms' distinguished 
        composing career are the short piano works he wrote late in his life.  The 
        six pieces Opus 118 were composed  in 1892 when Brahms was 59 years 
        old. No. 2, the Intermezzo in A major has endearing sentiment, and a 
        feeling of sweet sadness. It has one of the composer's most memorable 
        singing melodies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Intermezzo in B-flat, Op. 117, No. 2" componist="Brahms" midifile="096.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Some of the most moving works of Brahms' distinguished 
        composing career are the short piano works he wrote late in his life.  The 
        three pieces Opus 117 were composed  in 1892 when Brahms was 59 years 
        old. No. 2 Intermezzo in B-flat has moving melody which takes harmonic 
        turns filled with serene emotional colorings.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Intermezzo in E-flat, Op. 117, No. 1" componist="Brahms" midifile="095.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Some of the most moving works of Brahms' distinguished 
        composing career are the short piano works he wrote late in his life.  The 
        three pieces Opus 117 were composed  in 1892 when Brahms was 59 years 
        old. No. 1, the Intermezzo in E-flat  has a charming folk melody that must 
        be brought out from between a chordal accompaniment in both hands.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Intermezzo in c-sharp, Op. 117, No. 3" componist="Brahms" midifile="097.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Some of the most moving works of Brahms' distinguished 
        composing career are the short piano works he wrote late in his life.  The 
        three pieces Opus 117 were composed  in 1892 when Brahms was 59 years 
        old. No. 3, the Intermezzo in C sharp minor moves from a solemn, octave 
        melody opening to a bitter sweet middle section that can brings tears to 
        your eye.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Intermezzo in e-flat, Op. 118, No. 6" componist="Brahms" midifile="033.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Some of the most moving works of Brahms' distinguished 
        composing career are the short piano works he wrote late in his life.  The 
        six pieces Opus 118 were composed  in 1892 when Brahms was 59 years 
        old. No. 6, the Intermezzo in E flat minor is filled with mystery and 
        wonderful pianistic shadings. It builds to a powerful climax.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Rhapsody in g, Op. 79, No. 2" componist="Brahms" midifile="094.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Brahms' Rhapsody in G minor, Op. 79, No. 2 has been very popular over the years, and perhaps suffers
        a bit from over-familiarity. Still, there is much drama and worth to be found in this decidedly German romantic 
        music.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Waltz in A-flat, Op. 39, No. 15" componist="Brahms" midifile="045.MID" photo="brahms.jpg">
        Brahms' Waltz in A flat, Op. 3, No. 15, was published in September 
        1866 as part of Waltzer fuer das Pianoforte zu vier Haenden. The waltzes 
        were composed in 1865.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Automne (Etude de concert), Op. 35, No. 2" componist="Chaminade" midifile="120.MID" photo="chaminade.jpg">
        Cecile Chaminade (b. Paris 1857; d Monte Carlo, 1944) was a
        pianist and composer known for her graceful "salon" piano music. She was 
        a student of French violinist and composer Benjamin Godard and began 
        composing at the age of eight. From 1875, she began to give regular piano 
        recitals, including her own compositions. Her compositions include comic 
        opera, ballet, orchestral suites, a concert piece for piano and orchestra. Her 
        many piano pieces include Automne (Etude de concert), Op. 35, No. 2. Its 
        sentimental melody has made it popular.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Ballade No. 1 in g, Op. 23" componist="Chopin" midifile="010.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Ballade No. 1. Chopin's four Ballades are very special 
        works for the piano. They blend poetry and brilliance, drama and 
        tenderness, and all the wonderful musical qualities that people have come 
        to love in Chopin. They also display a unique construction that pulls the 
        listener into the story and keeps him spellbound throughout.
         The first Ballade in g is one of the most frequently heard. From its 
        opening dramatic octaves, through its heart throb melodies, to its bravura 
        passages, the musical expression is direct and effective.  
    </piece>
    <piece name="Barcarolle, Op. 60" componist="Chopin" midifile="008.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's only Baracarolle, Opus 60, was written 1845-6 and is one 
        of his finest compositions. The Barcarolle, at the time, was supposed to be 
        reminiscent of the kind of songs that Venetian gondoliers sang to their 
        patrons as they taxied through through the city's canals. Those songs have 
        long disappeared, but one can imagine the feeling of ease and flowing 
        grace mixed into the opening of this great work.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in A-flat, Op. 25, No. 1" componist="Chopin" midifile="027.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The melody of Chopin's Etude in A flat, Op. 25, No. 1 is revealed in 
        a series of scintillating arpeggios. This demonstrates Chopin's talent for 
        creating melody out of harmonies. 
         The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed when 
        Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The twelve 
        Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels of 
        composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes.
         
        Chopin's Etude in G sharp minor, Op. 25, No. 6 is considered by 
        most pianists to be very difficult because it contains liberal use of parallel 
        thirds.
         The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed when 
        Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The twelve 
        Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels of 
        composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in E, Op. 10, No. 3" componist="Chopin" midifile="012.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Etude in E, Op. 10, No. 3, was most likely modeled after a 
        vocal form of music. Its slow theme seems almost suitable for the human 
        voice, and is reminiscent of Italian opera. Curiously, the melody has found 
        its way into 20th century American pop music. When played with 
        simplicity and understatement, this etude is one of Chopin's most beautiful. 
        The lovely slow melody is interrupted by an animated and increasingly 
        chromatic forceful middle section.
         The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed when 
        Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The twelve 
        Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels of 
        composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in G-flat, Op. 10, No. 5 (Black Key)" componist="Chopin" midifile="009.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Etude in G-flat, op. 10, no. 5 (the so-called "Black Note" 
        Etude) is played largely on the black keys of the piano. The music is fast 
        and brilliant, with an enthralling cascading effect in the right hand, 
        punctuated by rhythmic chords in the left, which rivets your attention from 
        beginning to end. 
         The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed when 
        Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The twelve 
        Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels of 
        composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in a, op.25, no.11" componist="Chopin" midifile="214.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed 
        when Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The 
        twelve Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels 
        of composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes.
         The Etude in A minor, op. 25, no. 11 has been nicknamed the "Wind 
        Study" because of the swirling chromatic figuration in the right hand. 
        Rhythmic left hand chords and melody hold everything together. While not 
        easy, the music sounds more difficult than it actually is.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in c, Op. 10, No. 12 (Revolutionary)" componist="Chopin" midifile="029.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The dramatic, surging scales of Chopin's Etude in C minor, Op. 10, 
        No. 12 (the "Revolutionary") are intended to incite revolutionary feelings. 
        It was written soon after the Russians took Poland in 1831. The study 
        expresses first Chopin's sadness, then his anger at the cature of his 
        homeland.
         The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed when 
        Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The twelve 
        Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels of 
        composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in c-sharp, Op. 25, No. 7 (Cello)" componist="Chopin" midifile="030.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Etude in C sharp minor, Op. 25, No. 7 is often referred to 
        as the "Cello Etude". The left hand plays a broad melody, while another 
        makes its entrance in the right hand. The effect of this is a beautiful 
        interplay between the two themes.
         The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed when 
        Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The twelve 
        Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels of 
        composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in g-sharp, Op. 25, No. 6" componist="Chopin" midifile="028.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Etude in G sharp minor, Op. 25, No. 6 is considered by 
        most pianists to be very difficult because it contains liberal use of parallel 
        thirds.
         The twelve etudes of Opus 10 were written 1829-32 (and completed when 
        Chopin was only 22 years old). They were published in 1833. The twelve 
        Opus 25 etudes were composed from 1832-6. They are all marvels of 
        composition and unique in the way Chopin has managed to parcel 
        exercises in specific technical difficulties into a fully integreted and artistic 
        miniature of music. They are such remarkable pieces of music that it is 
        impossible to think of theme as mere etudes. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fantaisie-Impromptu in c-sharp, Op. 66" componist="Chopin" midifile="021.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
         Chopin's Impromptus are not considered to be his best work 
        because they can not match the substance of the Etudes and the Preludes. 
        However, of the four Impromptus written by Chopin, the Fantasie-
        Impromptu in C sharp minor, Op. 66 is considered to be the most 
        passionate. It was composed in 1835 (when Chopin was 25 years old) and 
        first published 1855.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Mazurka in B-flat, Op. 7, No. 1" componist="Chopin" midifile="090.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Although the Mazurka was a traditional Polish country dance, 
        Chopin stylized it into a refined concert piece with the essential rhythmic 
        spirit and elements of melody from the original.
         The Mazurka in B flat, Op. 7, No. 1 has a lively, melodically soaring 
        opening theme, contrasting only briefly by a mysterious sotto voce section.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Mazurka in b, Op. 33, No. 4" componist="Chopin" midifile="092.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Although the Mazurka was a traditional Polish country dance, 
        Chopin stylized it into a refined concert piece with the essential rhythmic 
        spirit and elements of melody from the original.
         The Mazurka in B minor, Op. 33, No. 4 is one of the easier ones to play. 
        However, Chopin offers the interpreter many emotional shades to play 
        with, and the haunting melody sits easily in one's memory. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Mazurka in c-sharp, Op. 63, No. 3" componist="Chopin" midifile="091.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Although the Mazurka was a traditional Polish country dance, 
        Chopin stylized it into a refined concert piece with the essential rhythmic 
        spirit and elements of melody from the original.
         The Mazurka in C sharp minor, Op. 63, No. 3 has a rhythmic simplicity 
        that makes it technically easier to play than many. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Mazurka in f-sharp, Op. 6, No. 1" componist="Chopin" midifile="089.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Although the Mazurka was a traditional Polish country dance, 
        Chopin stylized it into a refined concert piece with the essential rhythmic 
        spirit and elements of melody from the original. 
         The Mazurka in F sharp minor, Op. 6, No. 1 has a wistful, almost 
        harmonically enigmatic style which is bewitching.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Nocturne in B, Op. 32, No. 1" componist="Chopin" midifile="024.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Nocturnes have a special beauty which comes from their 
        slow, elegantly expressive right melodies and the rich supporting left hand 
        accompaniment. Chopin's Irish contemporary John Field (1782-1837) was 
        actually the first composer to write a "nocturne" (a work conveying the 
        mood of evening) for piano solo. Chopin modelled his after Field's.
         The Nocturne in B, Op. 32, No. 1 is one the most beautiful of these works. 
        Its melody and harmony are filled with interesting inflections and mood 
        twists. It seems to tell a story which remains a mystery almost right up to 
        its quickly dramatic close.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Nocturne in D-flat, Op. 27, No. 2" componist="Chopin" midifile="018.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Nocturnes have a special beauty which comes from their 
        slow, elegantly expressive right melodies and the rich supporting left hand 
        accompaniment. Chopin's Irish contemporary John Field (1782-1837) was 
        actually the first composer to write a "nocturne" (a work conveying the 
        mood of evening) for piano solo. Chopin modelled his after Field's. 
         In the Nocturne in D flat, Op. 27, No. 2, Chopin states the melody 
        differently three times. Each time, Chopin uses musical colour to vary the 
        effect of the melody. This technique is known as chromatic variance.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Nocturne in E, Op. 62, No. 2" componist="Chopin" midifile="026.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Nocturnes have a special beauty which comes from their 
        slow, elegantly expressive right melodies and the rich supporting left hand 
        accompaniment. Chopin's Irish contemporary John Field (1782-1837) was 
        actually the first composer to write a "nocturne" (a work conveying the 
        mood of evening) for piano solo. Chopin modelled his after Field's.
         The Nocturne in E, Op. 62, No. 2 begins and ends with a slow sostenuto 
        melody, sandwiching an agitated middle section.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Nocturne in E-flat, Op. 9, No. 2" componist="Chopin" midifile="017.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Nocturnes have a special beauty which comes from their 
        slow, elegantly expressive right melodies and the rich supporting left hand 
        accompaniment. Chopin's Irish contemporary John Field (1782-1837) was 
        actually the first composer to write a "nocturne" (a work conveying the 
        mood of evening) for piano solo. Chopin modelled his after Field's. 
         In the Nocturne in E-flat, op. 9, no. 2, Chopin repeats a melodic idea 
        several times. The intention of this repetition is to intensify the original 
        idea. Like many lyrical pieces of the time, this Nocturne is made up of 
        regular eight-bar periods.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Nocturne in F-sharp, Op. 15, No. 2" componist="Chopin" midifile="013.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Nocturnes have a special beauty which comes from their 
        slow, elegantly expressive right melodies and the rich supporting left hand 
        accompaniment. Chopin's Irish contemporary John Field (1782-1837) was 
        actually the first composer to write a "nocturne" (a work conveying the 
        mood of evening) for piano solo. Chopin modelled his after Field's. 
         In the Nocturne in F sharp, Op. 15, No. 2, Chopin begins with a Larghetto 
        melody whose simplicity is rippled with surprising twists of brilliance. The 
        middle section surges with increasing movement and sonority before the 
        languid opening melody returns.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Nocturne in g, Op. 37, No. 1" componist="Chopin" midifile="025.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Nocturnes have a special beauty which comes from their 
        slow, elegantly expressive right melodies and the rich supporting left hand 
        accompaniment. Chopin's Irish contemporary John Field (1782-1837) was 
        actually the first composer to write a "nocturne" (a work conveying the 
        mood of evening) for piano solo. Chopin modelled his after Field's.
         In the Nocturne in G minor, Op. 37, No. 1, Chopin's use of a dramatic 
        downward sweep at the beginning serves to increase the melancholy of the 
        piece, and sets a pensive mood.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Polonaise in A, Op. 40, No. 1 (Military)" componist="Chopin" midifile="106.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Polonaise in A, Op. 40, No. 1 is often referred to as the 
        "Military Polonaise" because of its brisk, march-like quality. Initially 
        bright and quick, it becomes broadly melodic toward the middle of the 
        piece. It was composed in 1838 and first published in 1840.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Polonaise in A-flat, Op. 53" componist="Chopin" midifile="093.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        In his Polonaise in A flat, Op. 53, Chopin repeats a melodic idea 
        several times. The intention of this repetition is to intensify the original 
        idea. Like many lyrical pieces of the time, this Polonaise is made up of 
        regular eight-bar periods. Regardless, there is no denying the stirring 
        power of this magnificent, ever popular work. It grips you from its 
        magnificent opening upward surges, to the rivetting left hand staccato 
        octaves, to the sonorous climatic chords. It was composed in 1842 and first 
        published in 1843.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in A, Op. 28, No. 7" componist="Chopin" midifile="049.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The twenty-four Preludes were composed from 1836-9 and first 
        published in 1839. Like Bach's Preludes from the Well-Tempered Clavier 
        (upon which these were modelled), Chopin composed one in each major 
        and minor key. Often the prelude is based on a single idea, sometimes only 
        a motive. They are true romantic miniatures, each pointedly expressing a 
        feeling or idea. They work as individual pieces, but when played as a set, 
        they display a true, cohesive emotional spectrum of the highest artistry.
         The Prelude in A, op. 28, no. 7 is the shortest of the set, lasting only 16 
        short bars. Its very brevity makes it a challenge to interpret.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in D-flat, Op. 28, No. 15 (Raindrop)" componist="Chopin" midifile="050.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The twenty-four Preludes were composed from 1836-9 and first 
        published in 1839. Like Bach's Preludes from the Well-Tempered Clavier 
        (upon which these were modelled), Chopin composed one in each major 
        and minor key. Often the prelude is based on a single idea, sometimes only 
        a motive. They are true romantic miniatures, each pointedly expressing a 
        feeling or idea. They work as individual pieces, but when played as a set, 
        they display a true, cohesive emotional spectrum of the highest artistry.
         The dripping of rain outside his study window is supposed to have given 
        Chopin the idea for the repeated notes in his Prelude in D flat, op. 28, no. 
        15 (the "Raindrop"). The repeated notes of this Prelude suggest the steady 
        drumming of raindrops on the roof. Listen for the passages representing 
        the storm's rolling thunder. The piece was written in Majorca in 1838.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in b, op. 28, no. 5" componist="Chopin" midifile="202.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The twenty-four Preludes were composed from 1836-9 and first 
        published in 1839. Like Bach's Preludes from the Well-Tempered Clavier 
        (upon which these were modelled), Chopin composed one in each major 
        and minor key. Often the prelude is based on a single idea, sometimes only 
        a motive. They are true romantic miniatures, each pointedly expressing a 
        feeling or idea. They work as individual pieces, but when played as a set, 
        they display a true, cohesive emotional spectrum of the highest artistry.
         The Prelude in B minor, op. 28, no. 6 has been nicknamed the "Cello" 
        Prelude because of its left hand melody. It has in fact been arranged for 
        cello with piano accompaniment, and it is indeed easy for the pianist to 
        imagine the tonal qualities and phrasing of a cello as he plays the melody.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in e, op. 28, no. 4" componist="Chopin" midifile="201.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The twenty-four Preludes were composed from 1836-9 and first 
        published in 1839. Like Bach's Preludes from the Well-Tempered Clavier 
        (upon which these were modelled), Chopin composed one in each major 
        and minor key. Often the prelude is based on a single idea, sometimes only 
        a motive. They are true romantic miniatures, each pointedly expressing a 
        feeling or idea. They work as individual pieces, but when played as a set, 
        they display a true, cohesive emotional spectrum of the highest artistry.
         Prelude No. 4 in E minor is a simple, sadly expressive melody floating 
        over repeated left hand chords.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in f-sharp, op. 28, no. 8" componist="Chopin" midifile="204.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        The twenty-four Preludes were composed from 1836-9 and first 
        published in 1839. Like Bach's Preludes from the Well-Tempered Clavier 
        (upon which these were modelled), Chopin composed one in each major 
        and minor key. Often the prelude is based on a single idea, sometimes only 
        a motive. They are true romantic miniatures, each pointedly expressing a 
        feeling or idea. They work as individual pieces, but when played as a set, 
        they display a true, cohesive emotional spectrum of the highest artistry.
         No. 8 in F-sharp minor is one of the more technically difficult of the 
        Preludes. The right hand must ring out a thumb melody amidst an 
        incessant cascade of rapid notes. There is no let up in intensity from 
        beginning to end.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Scherzo in c-sharp" componist="Chopin" midifile="124.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Scherzo No. 3 in C sharp minor was composed around 
        1839. Unlike the typical scherzo found as a movement in symphonies and 
        sonatas by Beethoven, Chopin's Scherzos are unique compositions, filled 
        with drama, tragedy and inspiration. In No. 3, the opening bare octave 
        principal theme rivets your attention. When he reaches the chords of the 
        Meno Mosso, the glittering cascade of falling broken chords creates a 
        magical effect. While this is not the most technically demanding of 
        Chopin's major works, it has an originallity and persuasive narrative power 
        which is enduring.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Waltz in D-flat, Op. 64, No. 1 (Minute)" componist="Chopin" midifile="011.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        In many ways, Chopin's treatment of the waltz is akin to the way 
        Baroque composers treated the court dances of their time. The layout of the 
        music is simple, the music elegant and charming, but the waltzes are not 
        intended to be great artistic statements. 
         Also nicknamed the "Dog Waltz", Chopin's Waltz in D-flat, op. 64, no. 1 
        (the "Minute Waltz") is supposed to take only one minute to perform. This 
        animated waltz, despite its nickname, is longer than a minute. Composed 
        between 1846-7 and first published in 1847, this waltz is one of Chopin's 
        most famous compositions.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Waltz in E-flat, Op. 18" componist="Chopin" midifile="118.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        In many ways, Chopin's treatment of the waltz is akin to the way 
        Baroque composers treated the court dances of their time. The layout of the 
        music is simple, the music elegant and charming, but the waltzes are not 
        intended to be great artistic statements. 
         The Waltz in E flat, Op. 18 opens with a trumpet-like fanfare and than 
        vigorously steps right into the swing of things. The leggieremente second 
        melody with its repeated notes is delightful. This one of the most brilliant 
        of all the waltzes.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Waltz in c-sharp, Op. 64, No. 2" componist="Chopin" midifile="019.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        In many ways, Chopin's treatment of the waltz is akin to the way 
        Baroque composers treated the court dances of their time. The layout of the 
        music is simple, the music elegant and charming, but the waltzes are not 
        intended to be great artistic statements. 
         The Waltz in C sharp minor, Op. 64, No. 2 is very popular. It's memorable 
        features include the sparkling right hand refrain that returns repeatedly, 
        and a particularly moving second melody. The overall musical effect is 
        more satisfying than most of his other waltzes. It was composed between 
        1846-7 and first published in 1847.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Waltz in e, Op. Posth." componist="Chopin" midifile="020.MID" photo="chopin.jpg">
        Chopin's Waltz in E minor, Op. Posth. is a quick a capricious piece 
        of fluff. Its rhythmic grazioso opening theme is introduced by an arpeggio-
        like pattern which begins low and quickly rises four octaves. There is a 
        lovely contrasting dolce melody before the opening theme returns and 
        scampers to the end.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Arabesque No. 1 in E" componist="Debussy" midifile="006.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Published in 1888, Debussy's Deux Arabesques (Two Arabesques) 
        have grace and charm, reflecting the style of the Romantic salon piece. 
        Debussy's Arabesque No. 1 in E has an easy, flowing grace. It has been a 
        popular choice, and a rhythmic challenge, for many piano students.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Arabesque No. 2 in G" componist="Debussy" midifile="007.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Published in 1888, Debussy's Deux Arabesques (Two Arabesques) 
        have grace and charm, reflecting the style of the Romantic salon piece. 
        Arabesque No. 2 in G is the more playful and brilliant of the two. The 
        rhythmic motif which opens and then dominates the music is quick, 
        incisive, and the right hand must scurry and hop about the keyboard with 
        lightness and clarity.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Clair de lune" componist="Debussy" midifile="004.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Debussy's Clair de lune was once called the world's most famous 
        piano piece. It was published in May or June 1905 as the third piece in the 
        Suite bergamasque. It may have been composed as early as 1890. The title 
        recalls the poem by Paul Verlaine, which was set to music by Gabriel Faure 
        (also included in The Pianist). Listening to the dream-like melody, and 
        lilting rhythm, one can imagine a young couple waltzing in the moonlight.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Danse" componist="Debussy" midifile="088.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Debussy's Danse is one of his finest early compositions. Its simple name hardly hints at the brilliance of
        this difficult piece, filled with cross rhythms, fast repeated chords and an exciting climax. It was first 
        published in 1890.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Doctor Gradys ad Parnassum (Children's Corner" componist="Debussy" midifile="139.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Doctor Gradys ad Parnassum, the first piece in Debussy's Children's 
        Corner suite, is a humorous poke at the set of piano exercises by Clementi 
        of the same name. One imagines a child seated at the keyboard, diligently 
        practising the scale-like exercises, although it is itself a brilliant sounding, 
        delightful piece of music.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
         The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes).
        In Jimbo's Lullaby, the second piece in Debussy's Children's Corner 
        suite, Jimbo (actually, Debussy misspelled Jumbo) is a toy elephant. One 
        can imagine the animal taking clumsy steps in this little child's cradle 
        song.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
         The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes).
    </piece>
    <piece name="Golliwog's Cake Walk (Children's Corner)" componist="Debussy" midifile="145.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Golliwog's Cake Walk, the last piece in Debussy's Children's Corner 
        suite, describes a wind-up mechanical toy, although this piece conjures up 
        visions of the American "minstrel shows" popular in Paris at the time.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
          The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes).
    </piece>
    <piece name="Jimbo's Lullaby (Children's Corner)" componist="Debussy" midifile="140.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        In Jimbo's Lullaby, the second piece in Debussy's Children's Corner 
        suite, Jimbo (actually, Debussy misspelled Jumbo) is a toy elephant. One 
        can imagine the animal taking clumsy steps in this little child's cradle 
        song.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
         The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes).
    </piece>
    <piece name="Reflections in the Water" componist="Debussy" midifile="082.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Reflets dans l'eau (Reflections in the Water) is one of Debussy's masterpieces for the piano. It is part of 
        his set of pieces called Images (book one), composed in 1905 when the composer was 43 years old. One can 
        imagine flecks of sunlight glittering on the waves. Beneath the surface, however, is a carefully crafted and 
        balanced gem of music.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Reverie" componist="Debussy" midifile="047.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Debussy was one of the finest composers of piano music. Reverie, written in 1890 when the composer
        was 28 years old, is hardly one of his most serious works. But its beautiful and soothing melody has moved 
        many hearts. Many people are familiar with the orchestral arrangement.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Serenade for the Doll (Children's Corner)" componist="Debussy" midifile="141.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Serenade for the Doll, the third piece in Debussy's Children's Corner 
        suite, is a tribute to the composer's daughter Chou-Chou's most prized 
        possession.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
         The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes).
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Engulfed Cathedral" componist="Debussy" midifile="046.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        La cathedrale engloutie (The Engulfed Cathedral), from Book One 
        of Debussy's Preludes, is drawn from the world of legend. It is probably 
        inspired by the story of the legendary kingdom of Ys, a tale which Edouard 
        Lalo expanded and turned into his opera Le Roi d'Ys. Debussy uses a series 
        of parallel fifths and octaves to give a mystical feeling. An undulating 
        motive in the piano's lower register suggests swirling waters. With a 
        mighty surge the cathedral rises out of the sea. Chantlike melody is heard 
        before the cathedral returns to its watery home.
         Debussy's Preludes are made up of two books of short pieces, the first book 
        composed in 1910 and the second from 1910-13. They are fine examples of 
        the composer's ability to vividly describe things of both real and imaginary 
        worlds in music. Preludes were a popular type of piano composition from 
        the Romantic period onwards. Inspired by the Preludes and Fugues by J.S. 
        Bach, the Prelude became a complete piece (rather than an introduction to 
        something else). Composers such as Chopin, Debussy and Rachmaninov 
        wrote many examples of these descriptive gems.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Girl With The Flaxen Hair" componist="Debussy" midifile="005.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        La fille aux cheveux de lin (The Girl with the Flaxen Hair) is from 
        Debussy's collection of Preludes for the piano. This lovely miniature has a 
        wistful, dream-like melody and gently persuasive harmonies. Debussy's 
        Preludes are made up of two books of short pieces, the first book composed 
        in 1910 and the second from 1910-13. They are fine examples of the 
        composer's ability to vividly describe things of both real and imaginary 
        worlds in music. Preludes were a popular type of piano composition from 
        the Romantic period onwards. Inspired by the Preludes and Fugues by J.S. 
        Bach, the Prelude became a complete piece (rather than an introduction to 
        something else). Composers such as Chopin, Debussy and Rachmaninov 
        wrote many examples of these descriptive gems.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Little Shepherd (Children's Corner)" componist="Debussy" midifile="144.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Debussy's The Little Shepherd is the fifth piece from the Children's 
        Corner suite. It is a description of another of the composer's daughter 
        Chou-Chou's toys.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
         The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes). 
        Golliwog's Cake Walk, the last piece in Debussy's Children's Corner 
        suite, describes a wind-up mechanical toy, although this piece conjures up 
        visions of the American "minstrel shows" popular in Paris at the time.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
          The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes).
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Snow is Dancing (Children's Corner)" componist="Debussy" midifile="143.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        The fourth piece in Debussy's Children's Corner suite, The Snow is 
        Dancing, is a vision of snowflakes dancing in the wind as a child looks out 
        the window.
         The Children's Corner suite (or Coin des Enfants) of six little piano pieces 
        was published in July 1908 and musically describes things from a child's 
        point of view. The front cover of the first edition had a drawing of an 
        elephant holding the string of a balloon or golliwogg, as well as a stamped 
        autograph of Debussy. Included is a dedication to the composer's daughter 
        Claude-Emma ("to my dear Chou-Chou, with the tender apologies of her 
        father for what is to follow"). 
         The suite was composed between 1906 and 1908, and performed in Paris 
        on Dec. 18, 1908. All the titles are in English (apparently "Anglomania" 
        was the rage in Paris at the time. Debussy's second wife Emma Bardac 
        insisted that Chou-Chou be raised by an English nanny and surrounded her 
        with English engravings of children's scenes).
    </piece>
    <piece name="Valse - La plus que lente" componist="Debussy" midifile="206.MID" photo="debussy.jpg">
        Debussy's La plus que lente is a swaggering, waltz-like salon piece. 
        There actually is a player piano recording of Debussy playing this himself! 
        It has little musical value except to entertain. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Pomp &amp; Circumstance No. 1" componist="Elgar" midifile="125.MID" photo="elgar.jpg">
        Sir Edward Elgar (1857-1934) named his set of 5 marches for 
        symphonic orchestra Pomp and Circumstance, quote Act 3 of 
        Shakespeare's Othello. Pomp and Circumstance No. 1 in D, op. 39 was 
        first performed in Liverpool in 1901. Today, it is more commonly known 
        as music for college graduations.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Claire de lune, Op. 46, No. 2" componist="Faure" midifile="116.MID" photo="faure.jpg">
        While Debussy's Claire de lune is considered one of the world's most famous piano pieces, the 
        composer was actually imitating a piece of the same name by Gabriel Faure. Faure's Claire de lune, Op. 46, 
        No. 2 is technically simple but has a lovely singing melody and sense of sadness.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Impromptu in F minor, Op. 31, No. 2" componist="Faure" midifile="086.MID" photo="faure.jpg">
        Faure's Impromptu in F minor, Op. 31, No. 2
    </piece>
    <piece name="Country Gardens" componist="Grainger" midifile="208.MID" photo="grainger.jpg">
        The melody for Country Gardens first appeared under that title in 
        The Quaker's Opera (printed in London, 1728). The tune was collected by 
        Cecil J. Sharp and Herbert C. MacIlwaine in 1907 as the Hankerchief 
        Dance, and it is Sharpe that Australian pianist/composer Percy Grainger 
        credits in the preface to his piano arrangement. 
         In his detailed performance notes, Grainger also mentions that he "rough-
        sketched for 2 whistlers and a few instruments about 1908" and "worked 
        out for piano, spring 1918". It is a delightful and perhaps best known 
        arrangement of this popular classic.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Irish tune from County Derry" componist="Grainger" midifile="101.MID" photo="grainger.jpg">
        In one of his British Folk-Music Settings, Australian pianist Percy 
        Grainger did great justice to the Irish tune from County Derry we more 
        commonly know as Danny Boy. He wrote this arrangement between 1902-
        11. His detailed performance notes on the printed music leave no doubt as 
        to his preferred interpretation.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Shepherd's Hey" componist="Grainger" midifile="102.MID" photo="grainger.jpg">
        One of his British Folk-Music Settings, Percy Grainger calls 
        Shepherd's Hey an English Morris Dance Tune, taken "from the playing of 
        the fiddler of the Bidford Morris Dancers (1906)" set for piano by him 
        using four variants. It is a silly bit of fluff, sure to pick up anyone's spirits.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Oriental" componist="Granados" midifile="126.MID" photo="granados.jpg">
        Granados' Oriental is from the composer's collection of 12 Danzas Espanolas (Spanish Dances), Op. 5.
        It is sombre with hauntingly memorable melodies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Air (Holberg)" componist="Grieg" midifile="149.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Grieg's Holberg Suite has achieved great popularity in its string 
        orchestra version. But it seems the piano version heard here is the original. 
        Grieg himself gave the first public performance in Bergen on December7, 
        1884. And in February 1885, he wrote to a friend that he had "set the poor 
        Holberg Suite for string orchestra. Perhaps it will not sound all that bad." 
         The fourth movement Air has a mournful melody and deliberate pacing.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Anitra's Dance (Peer Gynt)" componist="Grieg" midifile="153.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Composed as incidental music for Ibsen's play Peer Gynt, Grieg's 
        Peer Gynt Suite was originally conceived for orchestra (first performed in 
        1876)  and later arranged by the composer for piano duet and piano solo. 
        This First Suite, Op. 46, is the most famous.
         In the third movement, Anitra's Dance, Peer Gynt visits an Arab chieftain 
        in his tent on an oasis. Peer is in Eastrern dress, resting on cushions. 
        Anitra and a troupe of girls dance and sing for him.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Arietta, Op. 12, No. 1" componist="Grieg" midifile="084.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. Arietta, Op. 12, No. 1 is 
        a very short, cantabile melody with a middle accompaniment split between 
        the hands. This very first Lyric Piece was published in 1867.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Ase's Death (Peer Gynt)" componist="Grieg" midifile="152.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Composed as incidental music for Ibsen's play Peer Gynt, Grieg's 
        Peer Gynt Suite was originally conceived for orchestra (first performed in 
        1876)  and later arranged by the composer for piano duet and piano solo. 
        This First Suite, Op. 46, is the most famous.
         Ase's Death is No. 2 in the Suite. In it, Peer Gynt returns home from his 
        wanderings to be at the deathbed of his mother, Ase. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Elfin Dance, Op. 12" componist="Grieg" midifile="085.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. Elfin Dance, Op. 12, No. 
        4 alternates simple chords with a scampering eighth note melody. It was 
        published in 1867.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Gavotte (Holberg)" componist="Grieg" midifile="148.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Grieg's Holberg Suite has achieved great popularity in its string 
        orchestra version. But it seems the piano version heard here is the original. 
        Grieg himself gave the first public performance in Bergen on December7, 
        1884. And in February 1885, he wrote to a friend that he had "set the poor 
        Holberg Suite for string orchestra. Perhaps it will not sound all that bad." 
         The melody of the third movement Gavotte has become very popular. The 
        music has a happy lilt that carries into the little Musette second half.
    </piece>
    <piece name="I Love Thee" componist="Grieg" midifile="076.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        I Love Thee is a song written for Grieg's wife to be, Nina, and 
        transcribed for piano. It is a genuine outpouring of emotion.
    </piece>
    <piece name="In the Hall of the Mountain King (Peer Gynt)" componist="Grieg" midifile="154.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Composed as incidental music for Ibsen's play Peer Gynt, Grieg's 
        Peer Gynt Suite was originally conceived for orchestra (first performed in 
        1876)  and later arranged by the composer for piano duet and piano solo. 
        This First Suite, Op. 46, is the most famous.
         No. 4, In the Hall of the Mountain King, finds Peer at a wedding 
        ceremony. He abducts Ingrid, the bride of one of the villagers, and vanishes 
        with her in an invisible cloak. He quickly tires of her and sends her back 
        home. As he wanders about, Peer finds the royal hall of the legendary 
        Mountain-King, whose daughter falls in love with him. After Peer spurns 
        her, the enraged mountain-folk, trolls, elves and other magical creatures 
        show their displeasure in the ghoulish dances depicted in this music.
    </piece>
    <piece name="March of the Dwarfs, Op. 54, No. 3" componist="Grieg" midifile="015.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. March of the Dwarfs, Op. 
        54, No. 3 was published in 1891. It is an amusing and quite substantial 
        piece with a staccato bass line and exciting little swoops of melody in the 
        right hand.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Morning Mood (Peer Gynt)" componist="Grieg" midifile="151.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Composed as incidental music for Ibsen's play Peer Gynt, Grieg's 
        Peer Gynt Suite was originally conceived for orchestra (first performed in 
        1876)  and later arranged by the composer for piano duet and piano solo. 
        This First Suite, Op. 46, is the most famous.
         Morning Mood opens the Suite. It is a soothing pastorale that unfolds as 
        the sun rises.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Nocturne, Op. 54, No. 4" componist="Grieg" midifile="073.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. The Nocturne, Op. 54, 
        No. 4 was published in 1891. It has mildly intriguing harmony and some 
        light syncopation in the accompaniment figures.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Preludium (Holberg)" componist="Grieg" midifile="146.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Grieg's Holberg Suite has achieved great popularity in its string 
        orchestra version. But it seems the piano version heard here is the original. 
        Grieg himself gave the first public performance in Bergen on December7, 
        1884. And in February 1885, he wrote to a friend that he had "set the poor 
        Holberg Suite for string orchestra. Perhaps it will not sound all that bad." 
         The Preludium opens with exciting broken chords in the right hand while 
        the left hand sustains bass octaves. The broken chords maintain the energy 
        of the movement as fragments of lyrical melody are heard.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Rigaudon (Holberg)" componist="Grieg" midifile="150.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Grieg's Holberg Suite has achieved great popularity in its string 
        orchestra version. But it seems the piano version heard hear is the original. 
        Grieg himself gave the first public performance in Bergen on December7, 
        1884. And in February 1885, he wrote to a friend that he had "set the poor 
        Holberg Suite for string orchestra. Perhaps it will not sound all that bad." 
         The fifth movement Rigaudon is a spritely selection that sparkles from 
        beginning to end, interrupted only briefly by a more sombre Trio section.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sarabande (Holberg)" componist="Grieg" midifile="147.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Grieg's Holberg Suite has achieved great popularity in its string 
        orchestra version. But it seems the piano version heard hear is the original. 
        Grieg himself gave the first public performance in Bergen on December7, 
        1884. And in February 1885, he wrote to a friend that he had "set the poor 
        Holberg Suite for string orchestra. Perhaps it will not sound all that bad." 
         The second movement Sarabande has an expressive cantabile melody and 
        simple accompaniment.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Solvejg's Song, Op. 52, No. 4" componist="Grieg" midifile="072.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Grieg's Solvejg's Song, Op. 52, No. 4 is the story of Solvejg, a 
        beautiful village girl, and Peer Gynt. They declare their love for each other, 
        but he asks her to wait and goes off on his adventures. After many years, 
        he returns to her, ever faithful. She sings this tender song to him. "For to 
        whatever fate God's will may doom me, I love thee, dear, I love thee now 
        and for eternity."
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Bird, Op. 43, No. 4" componist="Grieg" midifile="075.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. The Little Bird, Op. 43, 
        No. 4 has a cute little trill figure in both hands. This short piece was 
        published in 1886.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Butterfly, Op. 43, No. 1" componist="Grieg" midifile="083.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. The Butterfly, Op. 43, 
        No. 1 was published in 1886. The clever little melody makes lets you 
        imagine a butterfly soaring than dipping in the wind.
    </piece>
    <piece name="To the Spring, Op. 43, No. 6" componist="Grieg" midifile="014.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. To The Spring, Op. 43, 
        No. 6, was published in 1886. It is short and very straightforward in style.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Wedding Day at Troldhaugen, Op. 65, No. 6" componist="Grieg" midifile="016.MID" photo="grieg.jpg">
        Edvard Grieg's most characteristic piano writing is found in his 
        many volumes of short works called Lyric Pieces. They reflect his strong 
        nationalism and one can find in them the folk music of Norway. They are 
        technically quite easy and also simply structured. Wedding Day at 
        Troldhaugen, Op. 65, No. 6 is probably the most well-known of all the 
        Lyric Pieces. It was published in 1897 and has a sparkling melody and 
        vigorous march-like rhythm. There is a wonderful climax with alternating 
        chords in both hands slowy building in loudness and reaching a series of 
        towering chordal bars before the opening theme returns.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in E-flat, Mvt. 1 (Hob.XVI/52)" componist="Haydn" midifile="155.MID" photo="haydn.jpg">
        The Sonata in E-flat, Hob. XVI/No. 52 was composed around 1794 
        and is one of Haydn's last piano sonatas. While he had tinkered with the 
        form throughout his lifetime and wrote many refreshing examples, this is 
        undoubtedly his masterwork. It is composed on grand scale far and above 
        all his others. In many ways, this may be considered the first true Piano 
        Sonata, that is, conceived for the bigger sonorities of the new fortepiano. 
         The first movement is huge proportions, right from the opening chords 
        through the marvellous development of the material.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in E-flat, Mvt. 2 (Hob.XVI/52)" componist="Haydn" midifile="156.MID" photo="haydn.jpg">
        The Sonata in E-flat, Hob. XVI/No. 52 was composed around 1794 
        and is one of Haydn's last piano sonatas. While he had tinkered with the 
        form throughout his lifetime and wrote many refreshing examples, this is 
        undoubtedly his masterwork. It is composed on grand scale far and above 
        all his others. In many ways, this may be considered the first true Piano 
        Sonata, that is, conceived for the bigger sonorities of the new fortepiano. 
         The second movement Adagio is more longer and more emotionally 
        moving that usual for Haydn. They is plenty of room for the performer to 
        find expression.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in E-flat, Mvt. 3 (Hob.XVI/52)" componist="Haydn" midifile="157.MID" photo="haydn.jpg">
        The Sonata in E-flat, Hob. XVI/No. 52 was composed around 1794 
        and is one of Haydn's last piano sonatas. While he had tinkered with the 
        form throughout his lifetime and wrote many refreshing examples, this is 
        undoubtedly his masterwork. It is composed on grand scale far and above 
        all his others. In many ways, this may be considered the first true Piano 
        Sonata, that is, conceived for the bigger sonorities of the new fortepiano. 
         The third movement Presto finale has great energy and pursues its climax 
        with vigour and determination. There is virtuosity, maturity and style in 
        abundance.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Entertainer" componist="Joplin, S." midifile="079.MID" photo="joplin.jpg">
        American rag-time composer and pianist Scott Joplin (1868-1917) 
        played in the brothels of St. Louis and Chicago before eventually settling in 
        New York city. His rags included the Maple Leaf Rag and the Wall Street 
        Rag, and he even wrote a rag-time opera (A Guest of Honour). Some credit 
        the revival of Joplin's music to American pianist/musicologist Joshua 
        Rifkin. It might have more to do with the 1973 hit movie The Sting, with 
        Robert Redford and Paul Newman, in which Joplin's The Entertainer 
        (1902) was featured.
    </piece>
    <piece name="In a Monastery Garden" componist="Ketelbey" midifile="121.MID" photo="ketelbey.jpg">
        English composer and conductor Albert Ketelbey (1875-1959) was 
        best known for orchestral works such as In a Persian Market and In a 
        Monastery Garden, which we hear now in piano version.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Ave Maria" componist="Liszt" midifile="122.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        Franz Schubert made a setting of Ave Maria based on a German 
        translation of Walter Scott's poem from The Lady of the Lake (1810). As 
        an accompaniment, he used the Prelude in C from Bach's Well-Tempered 
        Clavier, Book 1 (included in The Pianist). Franz Liszt later arranged this 
        piano version.
         
        Liszt's Mephisto Waltz, subitlted A Dance in the Village Inn, was 
        composed between 1858-61. In fact, Liszt seems to have been fascinated 
        with the Faustian legend, composing a second Mephisto Waltz 20 years 
        later, a Mephisto Polka a few years later still and even starting yet another. 
        All of it was inspired by the poem Faust by poet Nicholas Lenau. 
         The basic story is this: a peasant wedding is being celebrated in a village 
        inn when Mephistopheles and Faust, in disguise, enter. Faust is attracted to 
        one of the women but is too shy to make a move. The devil laughs, then 
        after critizing the musicians for playing too lethargically, grabs a fiddle 
        and begins to play. The dancing becomes wilder and wilder. Faust presses 
        the hand of the young woman, then together they dance out of the room 
        into the night and into the forest, as the devil's violin fades and becomes 
        mingled with the songs of nightingales. 
         As one might expect from the pen of history's great piano virtuoso, 
        Mephisto Waltz is a torrent of sensuous and demonic piano virtuosity.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Concert Etude No. 3 in D-flat (Un Sospiro)" componist="Liszt" midifile="056.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        Liszt's Concert Etude No. 3 in D flat, more commonly known as Un Sospiro, features a beauty melody 
        which rides on the crest of rolling arpeggios. It was composed in 1848
    </piece>
    <piece name="Hungarian Rhapsody No. 2" componist="Liszt" midifile="128.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        No. 2 is the most famous of Liszt's Hungarian Rhapsodies. Its familiar dramatic opening evolves into a 
        wide range of pianistic exhibitionism, both playful and virtuosic.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Liebestraume No. 1" componist="Liszt" midifile="053.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        Liszt composed three Liebestraum (or Dreams of Love) in 1850 when he was 39 years old. They are
        nocturnes and have a dreamy, romantic mood appropriate to the title. Liebstraume No. 1 in A-flat is prefaced 
        by a poem by Uhland: "Within Love's arms to bliss invited; To ye life's sweet enjoyments call: On me one 
        glance alone has lighted, Yet I am rich beyond you all. I yield Earth's joys without resistance, And as a martyr, 
        gaze on high, For over me, in golden distance, There opens a celestial sky."
    </piece>
    <piece name="Liebestraume No. 3" componist="Liszt" midifile="054.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        Liszt composed three Liebestraum (or Dreams of Love) in 1850 when he was 39 years old. They are 
        nocturnes and have a dreamy, romantic mood appropriate to the title. Liebstraume No. 3 in A-flat major with 
        its familiar melody is the most popular of the set. The accompanying poem by F. Freiligrath begins: "O love! O 
        love, so long as e'er thou canst, or dost on love believe; The time shall come, when thou by graves shalt stand 
        and grieve...."
    </piece>
    <piece name="Mephisto Waltz" componist="Liszt" midifile="123.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        Liszt's Mephisto Waltz, subitlted A Dance in the Village Inn, was 
        composed between 1858-61. In fact, Liszt seems to have been fascinated 
        with the Faustian legend, composing a second Mephisto Waltz 20 years 
        later, a Mephisto Polka a few years later still and even starting yet another. 
        All of it was inspired by the poem Faust by poet Nicholas Lenau. 
         The basic story is this: a peasant wedding is being celebrated in a village 
        inn when Mephistopheles and Faust, in disguise, enter. Faust is attracted to 
        one of the women but is too shy to make a move. The devil laughs, then 
        after critizing the musicians for playing too lethargically, grabs a fiddle 
        and begins to play. The dancing becomes wilder and wilder. Faust presses 
        the hand of the young woman, then together they dance out of the room 
        into the night and into the forest, as the devil's violin fades and becomes 
        mingled with the songs of nightingales. 
         As one might expect from the pen of history's great piano virtuoso, 
        Mephisto Waltz is a torrent of sensuous and demonic piano virtuosity.
    </piece>
    <piece name="On the Edge Of a Spring" componist="Liszt" midifile="058.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        Liszt's Au bord d'une source (On the Edge of a  Spring) is one of the finest works in Suisse, the first 
        book of Pilgrim Years (inspired by the composer's visits to Switzerland). It is a charming but difficult work. 
        The music seems to sparkle, with the melody notes plucked out of a delightful dance of notes. It was 
        composed in 1855.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Paganini Etude No. 3 (La Campanella)" componist="Liszt" midifile="127.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        La Campanella is the most famous of Liszt's six Paganini Etudes. Paganini, a contemporary of Liszt, 
        was of the great violin virtuoso of his time. Liszt arranged some of Paganini's violin etudes for the piano, 
        bringing an equivalent difficult and brilliance. La Campanella is a dazzling display of piano technique which 
        glitters particularly in the upper range of the instrument.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Valse Oubliee" componist="Liszt" midifile="059.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        The Valse Oubliee was written between 1881-85 when composer Liszt was in his seventies! It is a light 
        salon piece that dances with a touch of delightful virtuosity. Liszt composed three other works with the same 
        name.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Valse-Impromptu" componist="Liszt" midifile="057.MID" photo="liszt.jpg">
        Liszt's Valse-Impromptu in A-flat is a light salon piece with no serious intentions other than to 
        entertain and delight. It was first published in 1853.
    </piece>
    <piece name="To a Wild Rose, Op. 51" componist="MacDowell, E" midifile="048.MID" photo="macdowell.jpg">
        Edward MacDowell (1861-1908) was the first American composer to gain international recognition. 
        However, his compositions in the old German Romantic style (he lived in Germany for a time) was more 
        nostalgic than ground breaking. He is remembered mainly as a composer of small works. To a Wild Rose is 
        from his Ten Woodland Sketches, Op. 51 (1896). It has a simplicity and feeling of well-being that has made it 
        popular.
        The twenty-four Preludes were composed from 1836-9 and first 
        published in 1839. Like Bach's Preludes from the Well-Tempered Clavier 
        (upon which these were modelled), Chopin composed one in each major 
        and minor key. Often the prelude is based on a single idea, sometimes only 
        a motive. They are true romantic miniatures, each pointedly expressing a 
        feeling or idea. They work as individual pieces, but when played as a set, 
        they display a true, cohesive emotional spectrum of the highest artistry.
         The Prelude in A, op. 28, no. 7 is the shortest of the set, lasting only 16 
        short bars. Its very brevity makes it a challenge to interpret.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Andante &amp; Rondo Capriciosso, Op. 14" componist="Mendelssohn" midifile="034.MID" photo="mendelssohn.jpg">
         The Andante &amp; Rondo Capriciosso, Op. 14, with its wide variety of 
        technical challenges is one of Mendelssohn's most familiar works. The 
        Rondo is in a scherzo style, and a barrage of staccatos in 6/8 time. It is an 
        excellent example of Mendelssohn's clear keyboard writing style. The work 
        was published in 1833 although likely composed much earlier. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Song of Spring, Op. 62, No. 6" componist="Mendelssohn" midifile="070.MID" photo="mendelssohn.jpg">
        The Songs without Words (Lieder ohne Worte) continue the 
        Romantic tradition of writing short, lyrical pieces for the piano. Melodic or 
        lyric style is combined with harmonic, instrumental style. Mendelssohn 
        wrote a total of 48 Songs without Words, published in sets of six. Opus 62 
        was published in 1844.
         The Song without Words, Op. 62, No. 6 is entitled Song of Spring 
        (Fruehlingslied). It has an innocent charm which made it popular as the 
        background for cartoons (was that the loss of innocence?). You'll recognize 
        it immediately.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Song without Words, Op. 19, No. 1" componist="Mendelssohn" midifile="067.MID" photo="mendelssohn.jpg">
        The Songs without Words (Lieder ohne Worte) continue the 
        Romantic tradition of writing short, lyrical pieces for the piano. Melodic or 
        lyric style is combined with harmonic, instrumental style. Mendelssohn 
        wrote a total of 48 Songs without Words, published in sets of six. Opus 19 
        was composed between 1830-32.
         In the very first Song without Words, Op. 19, No. 1, Mendelssohn floats a 
        simple cantabile melody above a gentle accompaniment of broken chords 
        and a bass line.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Song without Words, Op. 38, No. 2" componist="Mendelssohn" midifile="068.MID" photo="mendelssohn.jpg">
        The Songs without Words (Lieder ohne Worte) continue the 
        Romantic tradition of writing short, lyrical pieces for the piano. Melodic or 
        lyric style is combined with harmonic, instrumental style. Mendelssohn 
        wrote a total of 48 Songs without Words, published in sets of six. Opus 38 
        was published in 1837.
         The engaging melody and rhythmically pulsating accompaniment of the 
        Song without Words, Op. 38, No. 2 will captivate you.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Song without Words, Op. 85, No. 1" componist="Mendelssohn" midifile="071.MID" photo="mendelssohn.jpg">
        The Songs without Words (Lieder ohne Worte) continue the 
        Romantic tradition of writing short, lyrical pieces for the piano. Melodic or 
        lyric style is combined with harmonic, instrumental style. Mendelssohn 
        wrote a total of 48 Songs without Words, published in sets of six. Opus 85 
        was published after the composer's death.
         The Song without Words, Op. 85, No. 1 has a gently rolling arpeggio 
        accompaniment with a simple, expressive melody.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Spinner's Song, Op. 67, No. 4" componist="Mendelssohn" midifile="069.MID" photo="mendelssohn.jpg">
        The Songs without Words (Lieder ohne Worte) continue the 
        Romantic tradition of writing short, lyrical pieces for the piano. Melodic or 
        lyric style is combined with harmonic, instrumental style. Mendelssohn 
        wrote a total of 48 Songs without Words, published in sets of six. Opus 67 
        was published in 1845.
         Composed in 1845, Mendelssohn's Spinner's Song (Spinnerlied) or Song 
        without Words, op. 67, no. 4 has also been nicknamed the "Bee's 
        Wedding". It begins with a Flight of the Bumblebees style swirl of 
        sixteenth notes and the energy continues throughout this substantial piece 
        of music.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Wedding March" componist="Mendelssohn" midifile="119.MID" photo="mendelssohn.jpg">
        When Mendelssohn composed incidental music to Shakespeare's 
        Midsummer Night's Dream, I'm sure he had no idea that thousands of 
        future couples would be using the 6th number to run down the church aisle 
        after their weddings. Apparently the trend started in England in 1847 and 
        got a further boost when Queen Victoria's daughter used it at Windsor in 
        1858. This piano arrangement should lift your spirits.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fantasy in c, K. 475" componist="Mozart" midifile="209.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        The Fantasy in C minor, K. 475, is one of Mozart's most astonishing works for solo piano. It covers an
        enormous range of emotion, from its starkly dramatic opening to typical Mozartian cheerfulness.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Fantasy in d, K. 397" componist="Mozart" midifile="051.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        Mozart's Fantasy in D minor, K. 397 is considered one of the composer's finest works for piano. It is
        not technically difficult to play. The beauty of this work is in the many contrasts of mood that Mozart 
        achieves.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in A, 1st Mvt., K.331" componist="Mozart" midifile="158.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        In Parisian style, this Mozart's Sonata in A, K. 331 begins with a 
        theme and variations movement. The theme and variations opening 
        movement replaces the Allegro which usually opens a traditional Sonata.
         Except for minor variations, the theme remains constant through the 
        movement, resulting in an expressive melodic line.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in A, 2nd Mvt., K. 331" componist="Mozart" midifile="159.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        In Parisian style, this second movement of this Mozart's Sonata in 
        A, K. 331 is a Minuet. The Minuet replaces the slow movement in the 
        middle of a traditional Sonata.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in A, 3rd Mvt. (Alla Turca), K.331" componist="Mozart" midifile="160.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        This final movement from Mozart's Sonata in A, K. 331, dubbed 
        "Alla Turca", is well known among music-lovers. It is a perfect example of 
        the French rondo, containing major and minor sections, and concluding 
        with a da capo.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in C, Allegro, K.545" componist="Mozart" midifile="161.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        Mozart's Sonata in C, K. 545, Movement 1. The Sonata in C, K.545, 
        was written by Mozart primarily as an instructional piece. It contains 
        elements of piano technique that Mozart expected his beginner students to 
        master. Nonetheless, it gives hints as to the brilliant nature of its composer.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in C, Andante, K.545" componist="Mozart" midifile="162.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        Mozart's Sonata in C, K. 545, Movement 2. The Sonata in C, K.545, 
        was written by Mozart primarily as an instructional piece. It contains 
        elements of piano technique that Mozart expected his beginner students to 
        master. Nonetheless, it gives hints as to the brilliant nature of its composer.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in C, Rondo, K.545" componist="Mozart" midifile="163.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        Mozart's Sonata in C, K. 545, Movement 3. The Sonata in C, K.545, 
        was written by Mozart primarily as an instructional piece. It contains 
        elements of piano technique that Mozart expected his beginner students to 
        master. Nonetheless, it gives hints as to the brilliant nature of its composer.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Variations on 'Ah, vous dirais-je, maman'" componist="Mozart" midifile="205.MID" photo="mozart.jpg">
        The melody which we commonly know as "Twinkle Twinkle Little Star" first appeared without words
        in 1761 as "Ah! Vous dirai-je, maman". While keeping in mind that Variations on a theme often reveals the 
        essence of a composer's creativity, it is fun to listen to Mozart's 12 Variations on this children's melody.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Ballet of the Unhatched Chickens (Pictures)" componist="Mussorgsky" midifile="168.MID" photo="mussorgsky.jpg">
        In the Ballet of the Unhatched Chickens (from Pictures at an 
        Exhibition), Mussorgsky was inspired for this piece by costumes designed 
        by Hartman for a children's play called "Trilby". Listen for the chickens 
        pecking at the inside of their shells.
         Mussorgsky's collection of piano pieces originally entitled "Katrinsky" or 
        "Pictures", was inspired by a set of paintings done by Russian artist Viktor 
        Alexandrovich Hartman. Mussorgsky and Hartman had worked closely to 
        regenerate Russian art, which they felt had become disunified with its 
        native country. After Hartman's death, Mussorgsky attempted to honor his 
        friend by transforming the paintings into music. The work, although the 
        finest of Mussorgsky's, was not published until five years after his death. 
        The popularity of the collection grew with its 1923 orchestration by 
        Maurice Ravel.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Bydlo (Pictures)" componist="Mussorgsky" midifile="167.MID" photo="mussorgsky.jpg">
        In Mussorgsky's Bydlo (from Pictures at an Exhibition), a "bydlo" is 
        a heavy Polish two-wheeled cart drawn by two oxen. As it approaches, its 
        sound gets louder. As the cart passes, the sound recedes.
         Mussorgsky's collection of piano pieces originally entitled "Katrinsky" or 
        "Pictures", was inspired by a set of paintings done by Russian artist Viktor 
        Alexandrovich Hartman. Mussorgsky and Hartman had worked closely to 
        regenerate Russian art, which they felt had become disunified with its 
        native country. After Hartman's death, Mussorgsky attempted to honor his 
        friend by transforming the paintings into music. The work, although the 
        finest of Mussorgsky's, was not published until five years after his death. 
        The popularity of the collection grew with its 1923 orchestration by 
        Maurice Ravel.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Promenade (Pictures)" componist="Mussorgsky" midifile="164.MID" photo="mussorgsky.jpg">
        The march-like Promenade (from Mussorgsky's Pictures at an 
        Exhibition) is repeated before the examination of each "picture" in the 
        exhibit. Each time it is played, it is subjected to different alterations and 
        moods.
         Mussorgsky's collection of piano pieces originally entitled "Katrinsky" or 
        "Pictures", was inspired by a set of paintings done by Russian artist Viktor 
        Alexandrovich Hartman. Mussorgsky and Hartman had worked closely to 
        regenerate Russian art, which they felt had become disunified with its 
        native country. After Hartman's death, Mussorgsky attempted to honor his 
        friend by transforming the paintings into music. The work, although the 
        finest of Mussorgsky's, was not published until five years after his death. 
        The popularity of the collection grew with its 1923 orchestration by 
        Maurice Ravel.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Old Castle (Pictures)" componist="Mussorgsky" midifile="165.MID" photo="mussorgsky.jpg">
        Mussorgsky's The Old Castle (from Pictures at an Exhibition) is 
        reminiscent of troubadour love songs. It paints the picture of a singing 
        minstrel in a castle courtyard.
         Mussorgsky's collection of piano pieces originally entitled "Katrinsky" or 
        "Pictures", was inspired by a set of paintings done by Russian artist Viktor 
        Alexandrovich Hartman. Mussorgsky and Hartman had worked closely to 
        regenerate Russian art, which they felt had become disunified with its 
        native country. After Hartman's death, Mussorgsky attempted to honor his 
        friend by transforming the paintings into music. The work, although the 
        finest of Mussorgsky's, was not published until five years after his death. 
        The popularity of the collection grew with its 1923 orchestration by 
        Maurice Ravel.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Tuileries (Pictures)" componist="Mussorgsky" midifile="166.MID" photo="mussorgsky.jpg">
        While in Paris, the painter found his subject in children playing in 
        the park of Tuileries. Listen for the children (represented by minor thirds) 
        singing in Mussorgsky's Tuileries (from Pictures at an Exhibition).
         Mussorgsky's collection of piano pieces originally entitled "Katrinsky" or 
        "Pictures", was inspired by a set of paintings done by Russian artist Viktor 
        Alexandrovich Hartman. Mussorgsky and Hartman had worked closely to 
        regenerate Russian art, which they felt had become disunified with its 
        native country. After Hartman's death, Mussorgsky attempted to honor his 
        friend by transforming the paintings into music. The work, although the 
        finest of Mussorgsky's, was not published until five years after his death. 
        The popularity of the collection grew with its 1923 orchestration by 
        Maurice Ravel.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Mouvement perpetuels" componist="Poulenc" midifile="210.MID" photo="poulenc.jpg">
        Poulenc's Mouvement perpetuels was composed in 1918. The three movements (Assez modere; Tres 
        modere; Alerte) are short and not difficult to play. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude, Op. 12, No. 7" componist="Prokofiev" midifile="117.MID" photo="prokofiev.jpg">
        The opening of Prokofiev's Prelude, Op. 12, No. 7 has a child-like sense of wonder and charm. There is 
        a sparkling background of notes while a melody in thirds threads its way through it all. There is a mechanical 
        middle section which is characteristic of the composer.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Flight of the Bumblebee" componist="Rachmaninov" midifile="052.MID" photo="rachmaninov.jpg">
        There have been many arrangements of The Flight of the Bumble 
        Bee, originally an orchestral interlude in Rimsky-Korsakov's opera The 
        Legend of Tsar Saltan (1900) but achieving more fame than the opera ever 
        did. Composers and performers have since relished its potential as a 
        virtuoso showpiece for all kinds of instruments. Rachmaninov wrote this 
        brilliant piano arrangement.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in c-sharp, Op. 3, No. 2" componist="Rachmaninov" midifile="044.MID" photo="rachmaninov.jpg">
        Serge Rachmaninov (1873-1843) is known today not only for his compositions but for his reputation as
        one of the finest pianists of the 20th century. His music is in the tradition of the Romantic period. There are 
        clear, memorable melodies and chromatic yet accessible harmonies. His Prelude in C sharp minor, Op. 3, No. 
        2 is one of his most popular short works. Its dramatic opening and towering chords envelope exciting passage 
        work.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Prelude in g, Op. 23, No. 5" componist="Rachmaninov" midifile="081.MID" photo="rachmaninov.jpg">
         Prelude in G minor, Op. 23, No. 5, is one of Rachmaninov's most popular pieces. Its repeated chords 
        create a huge range of sound on the piano.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Jeux d'eau (Fountains)" componist="Ravel" midifile="060.MID" photo="ravel.jpg">
        Of his Jeux d'eau (Fountains), Ravel wrote: Inspired by the noise of water, cascades, springs, the Jeux 
        d'eau is based on two motives, in the manner of first-movement sonata form without, however, conforming to 
        the classic tonal scheme." A weighty description indeed! Perhaps the preface to the published music is more 
        descriptive: "The river god laughing from the water which is tickling him." Composed in 1901, Jeux d'eau is 
        considered one of Ravel's finest works for piano.
        Bach's Minuet in G is from the Anna Magdalena Notebook, 
        composed by Bach for his second wife to help her with her harpsichord 
        lessons. It remains very popular with keyboard students to this day.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Menuet on the Name of Haydn (Sonatina)" componist="Ravel" midifile="080.MID" photo="ravel.jpg">
        Ravel's Menuet on the name of Haydn is the second movement of his Sonatine (1905). There is a
        warmth to the music which, combined with its simplicity, gives it undeniable charm.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Pavane For A Dead Princess" componist="Ravel" midifile="066.MID" photo="ravel.jpg">
        Ravel's Pavane, pour une infante defunte (Pavane for a Dead Infanta) is usually heard in the composer's 
        own orchestral arrangement. Ravel actually became increasingly unimpressed with this piece as he grew older, 
        and compared to his other fine works for the piano, it has no great formal or technical merit. It does, however, 
        have a captivating melody and harmonies which has moved many musical souls. It was composed in 1899.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Gymnopedie No. 1" componist="Satie, Eric" midifile="035.MID" photo="satie.jpg">
        Of Erik Satie's Three Gymnopedies (1888), No. 1 seems to convey a 
        mood of innocent wonder, in spite of its performance indication of "slowly 
        and mournfully". All of the Gymnopedies are curiously calming. One 
        smiles at Satie's footnote to the title calling them "ceremonial choral 
        dances performed at ancient Greek festivals".
         Erik Satie (1866-1925) seems to have been as enigmatic as his music. A 
        contemporary of Debussy (who he met in 1890), his economical writing 
        style, featuring simple melody and often unresolved harmonies, became 
        trendy among young Parisian composers beginning around 1910. An 
        interesting listen is Debussy's orchestral arrangement of the Gymnopedies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Gymnopedie No. 2" componist="Satie, Eric" midifile="036.MID" photo="satie.jpg">
        The instructions for Erik Satie's Gymnopedie No. 2 are "slowly and 
        sadly", perhaps befitting the "ceremonial choral dances performed at 
        ancient Greek festivals" known as the Three Gymnopedies (1888).
         Erik Satie (1866-1925) seems to have been as enigmatic as his music. A 
        contemporary of Debussy (who he met in 1890), his economical writing 
        style, featuring simple melody and often unresolved harmonies, became 
        trendy among young Parisian composers beginning around 1910. An 
        interesting listen is Debussy's orchestral arrangement of the Gymnopedies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Gymnopedie No. 3" componist="Satie, Eric" midifile="037.MID" photo="satie.jpg">
        Of Erik Satie's Three Gymnopedies (1888),  No. 3 seems the purest 
        and simplest because of its lack of any sharps or flats. It is marked "slowly 
        and solemnly" and calming sings it way through the white keys of the 
        piano. Like the other Gymnopedies, it has a hypnotic, bare bones left hand 
        accompaniment.
         Erik Satie (1866-1925) seems to have been as enigmatic as his music. A 
        contemporary of Debussy (who he met in 1890), his economical writing 
        style, featuring simple melody and often unresolved harmonies, became 
        trendy among young Parisian composers beginning around 1910. An 
        interesting listen is Debussy's orchestral arrangement of the Gymnopedies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in C, L.104, K.159" componist="Scarlatti" midifile="098.MID" photo="scarlatti.jpg">
        The Sonata in C, L. 104 is one of the most frequently performed of 
        Scarlatti's sonatas. It has a Spanish influence, using the spirit of Spanish 
        popular dance forms and is similar in style to a Spanish jota.
         Domenico Scarlatti (1685-1657) wrote over 500 pieces for the 
        harpsichord. Most of these pieces were adapted from the individual dances 
        of the suite. He published only 30 of these pieces in 1738 in a portfolio 
        called Exercises for Harpsichord (Essercizi per Gravicembalo). The one 
        movement pieces each have the title of Sonata. They were conceived not as 
        mere technical exercises, but real Etudes, in the sense of Chopin's works of 
        the same name. Although he was Italian born, his harpsichord works were 
        mainly composed in Spain, where Scarlatti spent the latter part of his life 
        under the patronage of Queen Maria B rbara. Each sonata is in one 
        movement with two optionally repeated sections. They often have a single 
        theme but sometimes two or three, and these melodies are concise, clear 
        and strikingly elegant. They often display the Spanish influence, not in the 
        lively dance spirit, but also in the use of note repetition, a characteristic of 
        Spanish guitar music. He imitates the strumming of a guitar with broken 
        chords. He also likes to set his basic melody against a steady rhythm, 
        echoing the tune around the keyboard. Scarlatti also likes to have the 
        melody thrown around in imitation between the two hands. He makes the 
        hands cross and, although he doesn't use a lot of melodic ornaments, has a 
        special love for trills. Today, these sonatas appear as piano solos, although 
        they truly are conceived for the sound of a harpsichord. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in F" componist="Scarlatti" midifile="099.MID" photo="scarlatti.jpg">
        Domenico Scarlatti (1685-1657) wrote over 500 pieces for the 
        harpsichord. Most of these pieces were adapted from the individual dances 
        of the suite. He published only 30 of these pieces in 1738 in a portfolio 
        called Exercises for Harpsichord. The one movement pieces each have the 
        title of Sonata. They were conceived not as mere technical exercises, but 
        real Etudes, in the sense of Chopin's works of the same name. They often 
        have a single theme but sometimes two or three, and these melodies are 
        concise, clear and strikingly elegant. They often display the Spanish 
        influence, not in the lively dance spirit, but also in the use of note 
        repetition, a characteristic of Spanish guitar music. He imitates the 
        strumming of a guitar with broken chords. He also likes to set his basic 
        melody against a steady rhythm, echoing the tune around the keyboard. 
        Scarlatti also likes to have the melody thrown around in imitation between 
        the two hands. He makes the hands cross and, although he doesn't use a lot 
        of melodic ornaments, has a special love for trills.
         The Sonata in F is one of the composer's most charming, with little 
        imitative drum-like passages and a tuneful melody. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sonata in d" componist="Scarlatti" midifile="100.MID" photo="scarlatti.jpg">
        Domenico Scarlatti (1685-1657) wrote over 500 pieces for the 
        harpsichord. Most of these pieces were adapted from the individual dances 
        of the suite. He published only 30 of these pieces in 1738 in a portfolio 
        called Exercises for Harpsichord. The one movement pieces each have the 
        title of Sonata. They were conceived not as mere technical exercises, but 
        real Etudes, in the sense of Chopin's works of the same name. They often 
        have a single theme but sometimes two or three, and these melodies are 
        concise, clear and strikingly elegant. They often display the Spanish 
        influence, not in the lively dance spirit, but also in the use of note 
        repetition, a characteristic of Spanish guitar music. He imitates the 
        strumming of a guitar with broken chords. He also likes to set his basic 
        melody against a steady rhythm, echoing the tune around the keyboard. 
        Scarlatti also likes to have the melody thrown around in imitation between 
        the two hands. He makes the hands cross and, although he doesn't use a lot 
        of melodic ornaments, has a special love for trills.
         The Sonata in D minor is one of the most popular with students. It has a 
        memorable melody and some charming upward scale runs in thirds. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Impromptu in A-flat minor, Op. 90, No. 4" componist="Schubert" midifile="105.MID" photo="schubert.jpg">
        Although Schubert had trouble with large scale works of music, he excelled in the creation of both 
        songs and short works for the piano, such as the Impromptus. His set of Impromptus, Op. 90 were composed 
        in 1828, just one year before his death. The Impromptu in A-flat minor, Op. 90, No. 4, maintains a background 
        of arpeggio-like chord patterns interspersed with singing melodies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Impromptu in E-flat, Op. 90, No. 2" componist="Schubert" midifile="103.MID" photo="schubert.jpg">
        Although Schubert had trouble with large scale works of music, he excelled in the creation of both
        songs and short works for the piano, such as the Impromptus. His set of Impromptus, Op. 90 were composed 
        in 1828, just one year before Schubert's death. The Impromptu in E flat, Op. 90, No. 2 flows with a seemingly 
        continuous scale melody that rolls up and down the keyboard. It has vigorous contrasting middle section and 
        coda.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Impromptu in G-flat, Op. 90, No. 3" componist="Schubert" midifile="104.MID" photo="schubert.jpg">
        Although Schubert had trouble with large scale works of music, he excelled in the creation of both 
        songs and short works for the piano, such as the Impromptus. His set of Impromptus, Op. 90 were composed 
        in 1828, just one year before his death. The Impromptu in G flat, Op. 90, No. 3, is a virtual song for the piano. 
        It is an exercise in sensitivity and tonal balance.
    </piece>
    <piece name="About Foreign Lands &amp; People, Op. 15, No. 1" componist="Schumann" midifile="175.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         About Foreign Lands and People (Von fremden Laendern und Menschen) 
        is the first of the set. It has a singing melody with a middle voice 
        accompaniment spread between both hands.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Almost Too Serious, Op. 15, No. 10" componist="Schumann" midifile="192.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Almost Too Serious (Fast zu ernst) is No. 10. The right hand syncopated 
        melody must keep a good balance with the bass accompaniment.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Arabeske, Op. 18" componist="Schumann" midifile="055.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        The Arabeske, Op. 18, is one of Schumann's less difficult works to play, but it has a substantial length 
        and lovely flow. In the middle is a more rigidly rhythmic contrasting section.
    </piece>
    <piece name="By the Fireside, Op. 15, No. 8" componist="Schumann" midifile="189.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         By the Fireside (Am Kamin)  is No. 8. Its singing eighth note melody 
        flows smoothly throughout. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Catch Me!, Op. 15, No. 3" componist="Schumann" midifile="179.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Catch Me! (Hasche-Mann) is No. 3 in the set. It scampers quickly along in 
        waves of staccatos and chordal accents.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Child Falling Asleep, Op. 15, No. 12" componist="Schumann" midifile="194.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         No. 12, Child Falling Asleep (Kind im Einschlummern) is one of the most 
        beautiful of the set. There is a gentle imitation between left and right hand, 
        and some exquisitely delicate harmonies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Curious Story, Op. 15, No. 2" componist="Schumann" midifile="177.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Curious Story (Kuriose Geschichte) is No. 2 in the set. It has good 
        humored, rhythmic chord passages interspersed with little stretches of 
        legato melody.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Frightening, Op. 15, No. 11" componist="Schumann" midifile="193.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Frightening (Fuerchtenmachen) is No. 11. It alternates between lyrical 
        passages and quick, rhythmic outbursts.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Important Event, Op. 15, No. 6" componist="Schumann" midifile="186.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Important Event (Wichtige Begebenheit) is No. 6 in the set. Its heavy 
        chords glow with the feeling of a pompous public ceremony.
    </piece>
    <piece name="In the Evening, Op. 12, No. 1" componist="Schumann" midifile="169.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Schumann used the term Fantasy Piece (Phantasiestueck) to describe 
        the many little piano works that portrayed his flights of fancy or flashes of 
        inspiration. The eight Fantasy Pieces, Opus 12, were composed in 1837 
        and are a marvellous display of Schumann's imaginative best. 
         In the Evening (No. 1, Das Abends) is a beautiful little gem with the 
        melody forming out of gentle cross rhythm in the accompaniment flow.
    </piece>
    <piece name="In the Night, Op. 12, No. 5" componist="Schumann" midifile="173.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Schumann used the term Fantasy Piece (Phantasiestueck) to describe 
        the many little piano works that portrayed his flights of fancy or flashes of 
        inspiration. The eight Fantasy Pieces, Opus 12, were composed in 1837 
        and are a marvellous display of Schumann's imaginative best. 
         In the Night (no. 5, In der Nacht) is considered one of Schumann's finest 
        short pieces. It combines seething energy and restlessness. It is the most 
        technically difficult of the set.
    </piece>
    <piece name="King of the Rocking-Horse, Op. 15, No. 9" componist="Schumann" midifile="191.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Knight of the Rocking-Horse (Ritter vom Steckenpferd) is No. 9. In this 
        fast paced piece, the middle voiced melody is accompanied by galloping, 
        rhythmic chords. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Perfect Happiness, Op. 15, No. 5" componist="Schumann" midifile="183.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Perfect Happiness (Glueckes genug) is No. 5 in the set. The surging right 
        melody is chased by an imitative left hand. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Pleading Child, Op. 15, No. 4" componist="Schumann" midifile="182.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Pleading Child (Bittendes Kind) is No. 4 in the set. The right hand shares 
        not only the melody, but also some of the accompaniment notes. The 
        ending chord is a curious unfinished twist.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Restless Dreams, Op. 12, No. 7" componist="Schumann" midifile="174.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Schumann used the term Fantasy Piece (Phantasiestueck) to describe 
        the many little piano works that portrayed his flights of fancy or flashes of 
        inspiration. The eight Fantasy Pieces, Opus 12, were composed in 1837 
        and are a marvellous display of Schumann's imaginative best. 
         Restless Dreams (No. 7, Traumes Wirren) is buoyantly energetic. The 
        right hand melody scurries about busily, while the left hand 
        accompaniment hops about. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Reverie, Op. 15, No. 7" componist="Schumann" midifile="187.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         Reverie (Traeumerei) is No. 7. Its slow sentimental melody has become 
        famous over the years.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Romanze in F-sharp, Op. 28, No. 2" componist="Schumann" midifile="074.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        The Romanze in F sharp, Op. 28, No. 2, is one of Schumann's more beautiful pieces. Its charming
        melody has made it a favorite.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Soaring, Op. 12, No. 2" componist="Schumann" midifile="170.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Schumann used the term Fantasy Piece (Phantasiestueck) to describe 
        the many little piano works that portrayed his flights of fancy or flashes of 
        inspiration. The eight Fantasy Pieces, Opus 12, were composed in 1837 
        and are a marvellous display of Schumann's imaginative best. 
         Soaring (No. 2, Aufschwung) is one of the most famous in the set. It 
        literally does soar, not only in the reaching of the melody but in the energy 
        of its rhythm.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Happy Farmer" componist="Schumann" midifile="115.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Froehlicher Landmann, von der Arbeit zurueckkehrend (The Happy Farmer Returning from Work) is 
        one of the most familiar and lively short pieces from Schumann's Album for the Young, Op. 68. All the pieces 
        are within the technical range of younger students but present mature musical problems.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Poet Speaks, Op. 15, No. 13" componist="Schumann" midifile="195.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
         Robert Schumann was known for writing sets of miniatures, each 
        painting a distinct character or psychological feeling. One of his most 
        beautiful sets, Scenes from Childhood (Kinderscenen), op. 15 was written 
        in 1838. What is unique is that Schumann has created music filled with 
        artistry and imagination, suitable in for the concert stage, that can at least 
        be technically approached by young students. The 13 selections are 
        individual pieces yet when played together and in order form a satisfying 
        whole.
         No. 13, The Poet Speaks (Der Dichter spricht) finishes the set in the spirit 
        of an operatic recitative, including a brief cadenza in the middle.
    </piece>
    <piece name="The Song's End, Op. 12, No. 8" componist="Schumann" midifile="114.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Schumann used the term Fantasy Piece (Phantasiestueck) to describe the many little piano works that
        portrayed his flights of fancy or flashes of inspiration. The eight Fantasy Pieces, Opus 12, were composed in 
        1837 and are a marvellous display of Schumann's imaginative best.
         The Song's End, Op. 12, No. 8, with its uplifting chords and happily rhythmic middle section, finishes the set 
        in good spirits.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Whims, Op. 12, No. 4" componist="Schumann" midifile="172.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Schumann used the term Fantasy Piece (Phantasiestueck) to describe 
        the many little piano works that portrayed his flights of fancy or flashes of 
        inspiration. The eight Fantasy Pieces, Opus 12, were composed in 1837 
        and are a marvellous display of Schumann's imaginative best. 
         Whims (No. 4, Grillen) bubbles with humor and energetic chord jumps.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Why?, Op. 12, No. 3" componist="Schumann" midifile="171.MID" photo="schumann.jpg">
        Schumann used the term Fantasy Piece (Phantasiestueck) to describe 
        the many little piano works that portrayed his flights of fancy or flashes of 
        inspiration. The eight Fantasy Pieces, Opus 12, were composed in 1837 
        and are a marvellous display of Schumann's imaginative best. 
         Why? (No. 3, Warum?) is short and the questioning can be heard in the 
        harmony itself. It has a lovely singing melody and counter melodies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Etude in c-sharp,op.2,no 11" componist="Scriabin" midifile="213.MID" photo="scriabin.jpg">
        Scriabin's Etude in C-sharp minor, op. 2, no. 1 (1887), while not a 
        difficult work, offers challenges in chordal balance and tonal color. It is a 
        strikingly beautiful little piece.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Romance in D-flat" componist="Sibelius" midifile="065.MID" photo="sibelius.jpg">
        Sibelius' Romance in D flat is one of Sibelius' more popular short salon pieces. It has a charm and
        lightness which is not really representative of most of the composer's works.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Valse Triste" componist="Sibelius" midifile="211.MID" photo="sibelius.jpg">
        Sibelius' Valse triste is a short salon piece with a truly melancholic opening mood, which switches 
        grudgingly to a smile in the middle.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Rustles of Spring, Op. 32, No. 3" componist="Sinding" midifile="002.MID" photo="sinding.jpg">
        Rustles of Spring (or Fruehlingsrauschen, composed 1896 and 
        published in 1909 as part of no. 1 of 6 pieces, opus 32) has been a popular 
        favorite and exists in many arrangements. Christian Sinding (1856-1941) 
        was a Norwegian composer and pianist who produced many compositions 
        ranging from songs to opera. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Arabian Dance (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="184.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         Arabian Dance is No. 5 in the suite. Imagine the little cymbals in the 
        backround, from behind silky veils, as this sensous little dance caresses 
        you.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Chinese Dance (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="185.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         Chinese Dance is No. 6 from the suite. Imagine the piccolo playing the 
        soaring, agile right hand melody. The simple, rhythmic left hand 
        accompaniment helps drive this short dance to its climax.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Dance of the Reed Flutes (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="188.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         Dance of the Reed Flutes is No. 7 in the suite. Tchaikovsky used a group 
        of flutes to play the right hand chordal melody. It has an easy charm, save 
        for a bit of serious excitement past the middle.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Dance of the Sugar-Plum Fairy (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="180.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy is No. 3 in the suite. You might want to set 
        your MIDI output to celeste or bells for this one. That's the way it sounds 
        in the orchestral version. This is a magical selection.
    </piece>
    <piece name="June (Barcarolle), Op. 37, No. 6" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="087.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's June, Op. 37, No. 6 is a Barcarolle for children. The 
        Barcarolle was a lilting, dance-like serenade that mimicked the songs of 
        Venetian gondoliers. This one is part of The Seasons, 12 characteristic 
        piano pieces for children that Tchaikovsky wrote between 1875-6. Each 
        piece represents a month of the year.
    </piece>
    <piece name="March (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="181.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         The energetic March is No. 2 in the suite. Listen for the scurrying little 
        "staccato e leggiero" section in the middle.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Mazurka, Op. 39, No. 10" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="043.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Aside from his Piano Concerto, little of Tchaikovsky's piano music 
        is heard these days. Unfortunately, the master of orchestral ballets never 
        garnered a reputation as a pianist and his output has been largely ignored 
        by performers. However, he did compose marvellous and charming little 
        pieces for children which offer the appealing qualities of his music without 
        the difficulty.
         The Album for the Young, Op. 39, made up of 24 little piano pieces, was 
        composed in 1878. Mazurka (No. 10) has the typical rhythm and touch of 
        sadness of the Polish dance.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Neapolitan Song, Op. 39, No. 18" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="041.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Aside from his Piano Concerto, little of Tchaikovsky's piano music 
        is heard these days. Unfortunately, the master of orchestral ballets never 
        garnered a reputation as a pianist and his output has been largely ignored 
        by performers. However, he did compose marvellous and charming little 
        pieces for children which offer the appealing qualities of his music without 
        the difficulty.
         The Album for the Young, Op. 39, made up of 24 little piano pieces, was 
        composed in 1878. Neapolitan Song (No. 18), with its carefree little left 
        hand staccato chord accompaniment, seems a little silly by modern tastes. 
        With the right attitude, you'll find it a sunny little charmer.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Old French Song, Op. 39, No. 16" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="042.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Aside from his Piano Concerto, little of Tchaikovsky's piano music 
        is heard these days. Unfortunately, the master of orchestral ballets never 
        garnered a reputation as a pianist and his output has been largely ignored 
        by performers. However, he did compose marvellous and charming little 
        pieces for children which offer the appealing qualities of his music without 
        the difficulty.
         The Album for the Young, Op. 39, made up of 24 little piano pieces, was 
        composed in 1878. Old French Song (No. 16) is well known to students of 
        the Suzuki Method of music instruction. An arrangement of this lovely 
        melody is one of the first pieces any Suzuki student learns. There is a touch 
        of sadness to the music and some lovely counter melodies in the left hand.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Overture (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="176.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         The Overture begins with sparkling energy and dancing chords, followed 
        by a busy, twisting little melody which is contrasted later by a sustained, 
        "dolce cantabile" melody.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Russian Dance (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="178.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         Russian Dance is No. 4 in the suite. It sizzles with energy from its opening 
        shot, through the heavy, left hand middle melody, to the big "crescendo" 
        finish!
    </piece>
    <piece name="Song of the Lark, Op. 39, No. 22" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="039.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Aside from his Piano Concerto, little of Tchaikovsky's piano music 
        is heard these days. Unfortunately, the master of orchestral ballets never 
        garnered a reputation as a pianist and his output has been largely ignored 
        by performers. However, he did compose marvellous and charming little 
        pieces for children which offer the appealing qualities of his music without 
        the difficulty.
         The Album for the Young, Op. 39, made up of 24 little piano pieces, was 
        composed in 1878. Song of the Lark (No. 22) is characterized by a 
        scampering little triplet "trill" figure and bright staccatos in the right hand. 
        The harmonies and the music are happy. 
    </piece>
    <piece name="Sweet Dream, Op. 39, No. 21" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="040.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Aside from his Piano Concerto, little of Tchaikovsky's piano music 
        is heard these days. Unfortunately, the master of orchestral ballets never 
        garnered a reputation as a pianist and his output has been largely ignored 
        by performers. However, he did compose marvellous and charming little 
        pieces for children which offer the appealing qualities of his music without 
        the difficulty.
         The Album for the Young, Op. 39, made up of 24 little piano pieces, was 
        composed in 1878. Sweet Dream (No. 21) is marked with the indication 
        "with great feeling". The melody surges forward with insistent support 
        from the harmonies. There is a nice touch of that typical Russian bitter 
        sweetness.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Waltz of the Flowers (Nutcracker)" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="190.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker (composed 1891-2) is one of the 
        composer's most successful and enduring ballets. In 1892, Tchaikovsky 
        constructed an orchestral suite or collection of dance movements from the 
        Nutcracker, Op. 71a, which is heard here in the piano solo version.
         Waltz of the Flowers (No. 8) is the finale of the suite. It has big 
        introduction, with the harp-like cadenza setting up the waltz introduction. 
        You'll find yourself humming the familiar melodies.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Waltz, Op. 39, No. 8" componist="Tchaikovsky" midifile="038.MID" photo="tchaikovsky.jpg">
        Aside from his Piano Concerto, little of Tchaikovsky's piano music 
        is heard these days. Unfortunately, the master of orchestral ballets never 
        garnered a reputation as a pianist and his output has been largely ignored 
        by performers. However, he did compose marvellous and charming little 
        pieces for children which offer the appealing qualities of his music without 
        the difficulty.
         The Album for the Young, Op. 39, made up of 24 little piano pieces, was 
        composed in 1878. Waltz (No. 8) is a moderately fast with momentum and 
        energy typical of some of his finer ballet waltzes.
    </piece>
    <piece name="Punch (Le Polichinelle)" componist="Villa-Lobos" midifile="129.MID" photo="villalobos.jpg">
        Villa-Lobos' Le Polichinelle (Punch) is an exciting little work with rapidly alternating hands, the right 
        hand playing white key chords, the left playing black keys. It is from his set of pieces called Prole do Bebe 
        (The Baby Dolls).
    </piece>
    <piece name="Rondo Brilliant in E-flat, op 62" componist="Von Weber" midifile="215.MID" photo="vonweber.jpg">
        Carl Maria Von Weber (1786-1826) has been largely ignored as a 
        serious composer, except for his operas, coming across as sounding 
        somewhat trivial. The Rondo Brillant in E-flat, op. 62 (1819) is a rapid fire 
        fantasy piece that has that "old-fashioned" elegance and technical variety 
        which can be pleasing to the ear. 
    </piece>
</thepianist>
